<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY RFC2104 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2104.xml" >
  <!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml" >

  <!ENTITY RFC2633 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2633.xml" >
  <!ENTITY RFC2898 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2898.xml" >
  <!ENTITY RFC3394 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3394.xml" >
  <!ENTITY RFC3447 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3447.xml" >
  <!ENTITY RFC3610 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3610.xml" >
  <!ENTITY RFC4231 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4231.xml" >
  <!ENTITY RFC4262 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4262.xml" >
  <!ENTITY RFC5480 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5480.xml" >
  <!ENTITY RFC5652 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5652.xml" >
  <!ENTITY RFC5751 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5751.xml" >
  <!ENTITY RFC5752 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5752.xml" >
  <!ENTITY RFC5869 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5869.xml" >
  <!ENTITY RFC5990 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5990.xml" >
  <!ENTITY RFC6090 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6090.xml" >
  <!ENTITY RFC6151 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6151.xml" >
  <!ENTITY RFC6979 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6979.xml" >
  <!ENTITY RFC7049 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7049.xml" >
  <!ENTITY RFC7159 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7159.xml" >
  <!ENTITY RFC7252 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7252.xml" >
  <!ENTITY RFC7515 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7515.xml" >
  <!ENTITY RFC7516 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7516.xml" >
  <!ENTITY RFC7517 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7517.xml" >
  <!ENTITY RFC7518 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7518.xml" >
  <!ENTITY RFC7539 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7539.xml" >

  <!ENTITY CDDL SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.greevenbosch-appsawg-cbor-cddl.xml" >
  <!ENTITY CBCMAC SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.mcgrew-aead-aes-cbc-hmac-sha2.xml" >
  <!ENTITY CFRG-EC SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.irtf-cfrg-curves.xml" >

<!ENTITY Triple-01 SYSTEM "includes/Triple-01.xml">
<!ENTITY Enc-01 SYSTEM "includes/Enc-01.xml">
<!ENTITY Enc-02 SYSTEM "includes/Enc-02.xml">
<!ENTITY Mac-01 SYSTEM "includes/Mac-01.xml">
<!ENTITY Mac-02 SYSTEM "includes/Mac-02.xml">
<!ENTITY Mac-03 SYSTEM "includes/Mac-03.xml">
<!ENTITY Mac-04 SYSTEM "includes/Mac-04.xml">
<!ENTITY Sig-01 SYSTEM "includes/Sig-01.xml">
<!ENTITY Sig-02 SYSTEM "includes/Sig-02.xml">
<!ENTITY PrivKeys SYSTEM "includes/private-keyset.xml">
<!ENTITY PubKeys SYSTEM "includes/public-keyset.xml">

]>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-ietf-cose-msg-latest" category="info">
  <front>
    <title>CBOR Encoded Message Syntax</title>

    <author initials="J." surname="Schaad" fullname="Jim Schaad">
      <organization>August Cellars</organization>
      <address>
        <email>ietf@augustcellars.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date/>

    <area>Security</area>
    <workgroup>COSE Working Group</workgroup>
    <abstract>
      <t>
        Concise Binary Object Representation (CBOR) is data format designed for small code size and small message size.
        There is a need for the ability to have the basic security services defined for this data format.
        This document specifies how to do signatures, message authentication codes and encryption using this data format.
      </t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Contributing to this document">
      <!-- RFC EDITOR - Please remove this note before publishing -->
      <t>
        The source for this draft is being maintained in GitHub.
        Suggested changes should be submitted as pull requests  at <eref target="https://github.com/cose-wg/cose-spec"/>.
        Instructions are on that page as well.
        Editorial changes can be managed in GitHub, but any substantial issues need to be discussed on the COSE mailing list.
      </t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>

    <section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">

      <t>
        There has been an increased focus on the small, constrained devices that make up the Internet of Things (IOT). 
        One of the standards that has come of of this process is the Concise Binary Object Representation (CBOR). 
        CBOR extended the data model of the JavaScript Object Notation (JSON) by allowing for binary data among other changes. 
        CBOR is being adopted by several of the IETF working groups dealing with the IOT world as their encoding of data structures. 
        CBOR was designed specifically to be both small in terms of messages transport and implementation size as well having a schema free decoder.
        A need exists to provide basic message security services for IOT and using CBOR as the message encoding format makes sense.
      </t>

      <t>
        The JOSE working group produced a set of documents <xref target="RFC7515"/><xref target="RFC7516"/><xref target="RFC7517"/><xref target="RFC7518"/> that defined how to perform encryption, signatures and message authentication (MAC) operations for JSON documents and then to encode the results using the JSON format <xref target="RFC7159"/>.
        This document does the same work for use with the CBOR <xref target="RFC7049"/> document format.
        While there is a strong attempt to keep the flavor of the original JOSE documents, two considerations are taken into account:
      </t>

      <t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            CBOR has capabilities that are not present in JSON and should be used. 
            One example of this is the fact that CBOR has a method of encoding binary directly without first converting it into a base64 encoded string.
          </t>
          <t>
            COSE is not a direct copy of the JOSE specification.
            In the process of creating COSE, decisions that were made for JOSE were re-examined.
            In many cases different results were decided on as the criteria were not always the same as for JOSE.
            <!--
                Hannes
                
                For a working group draft it does not matter whether the author agrees or disagrees. I would suggest to remove this paragraph.

                REPLACED TEXT:
                The author did not always agree with some of the decisions made by the JOSE working group. 
                Many of these decisions have been re-examined, and where it seems to the author to be superior or simpler, replaced.
            -->
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <section anchor="design-changes-from-jose" title="Design changes from JOSE">

        <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              Define a top level message structure so that encrypted, signed and MACed messages can easily identified and still have a consistent view.
            </t>
            <t>
              Signed messages separate the concept of protected and unprotected parameters that are for the content and the signature.
            </t>
            <t>
              Recipient processing has been made more uniform.
              A recipient structure is required for all recipients rather than only for some.
            </t>
            <t>
              MAC messages are separated from signed messages.
            </t>
            <t>
              MAC messages have the ability to do use all recipient algorithms on the MAC authentication key.
            </t>
            <t>
              Use binary encodings for binary data rather than base64url encodings.
            </t>
            <t>
              Combine the authentication tag for encryption algorithms with the ciphertext.
            </t>
            <t>
              Remove the flattened mode of encoding. 
              Forcing the use of an array of recipients at all times forces the message size to be two bytes larger, but one gets a corresponding decrease in the implementation size that should compensate for this.
              <cref source="JLS">Need to check this list for correctness before publishing.</cref>
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>

      </section>

      
      <section anchor="requirements-terminology" title="Requirements Terminology">
        <!--  NOTE FOR AUTHORS:
             We use the following terms in the document
             
             field - an entry in a CBOR array
             parameter - an element in a CBOR map (as oppose to 'member' which is frequently used in JSON
             label - the key of an element in a CBOR map.   Unless otherwise separated from text, enclose with single quote marks
             value - the value of an element in a CBOR map
        -->

        <t>
          The key words “MUST”, “MUST NOT”, “REQUIRED”, “SHALL”, “SHALL NOT”, “SHOULD”, “SHOULD NOT”, “RECOMMENDED”, “NOT RECOMMENDED”, “MAY”, and “OPTIONAL” in this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
        </t>

        <t>
          When the words appear in lower case, their natural language meaning is used.
        </t>

      </section>
      
      <section anchor="cbor-grammar" title="CBOR Grammar">

        <t>
          There currently is no standard CBOR grammar available for use by specifications.
          We therefore describe the CBOR structures in prose.
          There is a version of a CBOR grammar in the CBOR Data Definition Language (CDDL) <xref target="I-D.greevenbosch-appsawg-cbor-cddl"/>.
          An informational version of the CBOR grammar that reflects what is in the prose can be found in <xref target="Grammar_Appendix"/>.
          CDDL has not been fixed, so this grammar may will only work with the version of CDDL at the time of publishing.
        </t>

        <t>
          The document was developed by first working on the grammar and then developing the prose to go with it.
          An artifact of this is that the prose was written using the primitive type strings defined by early versions CDDL.
          In this specification the following primitive types are used:
          <list style="none">
            <t>bstr - byte string (major type 2).</t>
            <t>int - an unsigned integer or a negative integer.</t>
            <t>nil - a null value (tag 7.22).</t>
            <t>nint - a negative integer (major type 1).</t>
            <t>tstr - a UTF-8 text string (major type 3).</t>
            <t>uint - an unsigned integer (major type 0).</t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <!-- RFC EDITOR - Please make sure the following paragraphs have been removed. -->

        <t>
          Text from here to start of next section to be removed
        </t>
             
        <t>
          NOTE: For the purposes of review, we are currently interlacing the CDLL grammar into the text of document.
          This is being done for simplicity of comparision of the grammar againist the prose.
          The grammar will be removed to an appendix during WGLC.
        </t>
        
        <figure><artwork type='CDDL'>
<![CDATA[
start = COSE_Untagged_Message / COSE_Tagged_Message / COSE_Key / COSE_KeySet
]]></artwork></figure>

        
      </section>

      <section title="CBOR Related Terminology" anchor="label">
        <t>
          In JSON, maps are called objects and only have one kind of map key: a string.
          In COSE, we use both strings and integers (both negative and non-negative integers) as map keys, as well as data items to identify specific choices.
          The integers (both positive and negative) are used for compactness of encoding and easy comparison.
          (Generally, in this document the value zero is going to be reserved and not used.)
          Since the work "key" is mainly used in its other meaning, as a cryptographic key, we use the term "label" for this usage of either an integer or a string to identify map keys and choose data items.
        </t>

        <!-- RFC EDITOR - Please make sure the following paragraphs have been removed. -->

        <t>
          Text from here to start of next section to be removed
        </t>

        <figure><artwork type='CDDL'>
<![CDATA[
label = int / tstr
values = any
]]></artwork></figure>

      </section>

      <section title="Document Terminology">
        <t>
          In this document we use the following terminology:
          <cref source="JLS">
            I have not gone through the document to determine what needs to be here yet.
            We mostly want to grab terms which are used in unusual ways or are not generally understood.
          </cref>
        </t>
        
        <t>Byte is a synonym for octet.</t>
        <t>
          Key management is used as a term to describe how a key at level n is obtained from level n+1 in encrypted and MACed messages.
          The term is also used to discuss key life cycle management,  this document does not discuss key life cycle operations.
          <!-- Ilari OPEN
               Should we remove the term "KEY MANAGEMENT" in this location as well.

               JLS - perhaps we should do a discussion of how the term is used in different places and punt?
          -->
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Mandatory to Implement Algorithms">
        <t>
          One of the issues that needs to be addressed is a requirement that a standard specify a set of algorithms that are required to be implemented.
          <cref source="JLS">
            It would be possible to extend this section to talk about those decisions which an application needs to think about rather than just talking about MTI algoithms.
          </cref>
          This is done to promote interoperability as it provides a minimal set of algorithms that all devices can be sure will exist at both ends.
          However, we have elected not to specify a set of mandatory algorithms in this document.
        </t>

        <t>
          It is expected that COSE is going to be used in a wide variety of applications and on a wide variety of devices.
          Many of the constrained devices are going to be setup to used a small fixed set of algorithms, and this set of algorithms may not match those available on a device.
          We therefore have deferred to the application protocols the decision of what to specify for mandatory algorithms.
        </t>

        <t>
          Since the set of algorithms in an environment of constrained devices may depend on what the set of devices are and how long they have been in operation, we want to highlight that application protocols will need to specify some type of discovery method of algorithm capabilities.
          The discovery method may be as simple as requiring preconfiguration of the set of algorithms to providing a discovery method built into the protocol.
          S/MIME provided a number of different ways to approach the problem:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>Advertising in the message (S/MIME capabilities) <xref target="RFC5751"/>.</t>
            <t>Advertising in the certificate (capabilities extension) <xref target="RFC4262"/></t>
            <t>Minimum requirements for the S/MIME which have been updated over time <xref target="RFC2633"/><xref target="RFC5751"/></t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

    </section>
    
    <section anchor="the-cosemsg-structure" title="Basic COSE Structure">
      <t>
        The COSE Message structure is designed so that there can be a large amount of common code when parsing and processing the different security messages.
        All of the message structures are build on a CBOR array type.
        The first three elements of the array contains the same basic information.
        The first element is a set of protected header information.
        The second element is a set of unprotected header information.
        The third element is the content of the message (either as plain text or encrypted).
        Elements after this point are dependent on the specific message type.
      </t>

      <t>
        Identification of which message is present is done by one of two methods:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            The specific message type is known from the context in which it is placed.
            This may be defined by a marker in the containing structure or by restrictions specified by the application protocol.
          </t>
          <t>
            The message type is identified by a CBOR tag.
            This document defines a CBOR tag for each of the message structures.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      
      <!--
      <t>
        The COSE_MSG structure is a top level CBOR object that corresponds to the DataContent type in the Cryptographic Message Syntax (CMS) <xref target="RFC5652"/>.
        < ! - - Hannes
             I would remove references to CMS and S/MIME since they are most likely only helpful to a very small audience.

             OPEN
        - - >
        <cref source="Hannes">I would remove references to CMS and S/MIME since they are most likely only helpful to a very small audience.</cref>

        This structure allows for a top level message to be sent that could be any of the different security services.
        The security service is identified within the message.
        </t>

        <t>
        The COSE_Tagged_MSG CBOR type takes the COSE_MSG and prepends a CBOR tag of TBD1 to the encoding of COSE_MSG.
        By having both a tagged and untagged version of the COSE_MSG structure, it becomes easy to either use COSE_MSG as a top level object or embedded in another object.
        The tagged version allows for a method of placing the COSE_MSG structure into a choice, using a consistent tag value to determine that this is a COSE object.
        </t>

      <t>
        The existence of the COSE_MSG and COSE_Tagged_MSG CBOR data types are not intended to prevent protocols from using the individual security primitives directly.
        Where only a single service is required, that structure can be used directly.
      </t>

      <t>
        Each of the top-level security objects use a CBOR array as the base structure.
        For each of the top-level security objects, the first field is a 'msg_type'.
        The CBOR type for a 'msg_type' is 'int'.
        The 'msg_type' is defined to distinguish between the different structures when they appear as part of a COSE_MSG object.
        <cref source="JLS">
          I have moved msg_type into the individual structures.
          However, they would not be necessary in the cases where a) the security service is known and b) security libraries can setup to take individual structures.
          Should they be moved back to just appearing if used in a COSE_MSG rather than on the individual structure?
          This would make things shorter if one was using just a signed message because the msg_type field can be omitted as well as the COSE_Tagged_MSG tag field.
          One the other hand, it will complicated the code if one is doing general purpose library type things.
        </cref>
        <cref source="JLS">Should we create an IANA registries for the values of msg_type?</cref>
        <cref source="CB">I would like to make msg_type go away</cref>
      </t>

      <t>
        The message types defined in this document are:
        <list style="none">
          <t>0 - Reserved.</t>
          <t>1 - Signed Message.</t>
          <t>2 - Enveloped Message</t>
          <t>3 - Authenticated Message (MACed message)</t>
          <t>4 - Encrypted Message</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>
        Implementations MUST be prepared to find an integer in this field that does not correspond to the values 1 to 3.
        If a message type is found then the client does not support the associated security object, the client MUST stop attempting to process the structure and fail.
        The value of 0 is reserved and not assigned to a security object.
        If the value of 0 is found, then clients MUST fail processing the structure.
        Implementations need to recognize that the set of values might be extended at a later date, but they should not provide a security service based on guesses of what the security object might be.
      </t>
      -->

      <!-- RFC EDITOR - Please make sure the following paragraphs have been removed. -->

      <t>
        Text from here to start of next section to be removed
      </t>

      <figure><artwork type="CDDL"><![CDATA[

COSE_Untagged_Message = COSE_Sign / 
    COSE_enveloped /
    COSE_encryptData /
    COSE_Mac

COSE_Tagged_Message = COSE_Sign_Tagged /
    COSE_Enveloped_Tagged /
    COSE_EncryptedData_Tagged /
    COSE_Mac_Tagged
]]></artwork></figure>


      <!--
      <texttable anchor="Top-Level-Keys" title="COSE Map Labels">
        <ttcol align='left'>name</ttcol>
        <ttcol align='left'>number</ttcol>
        <ttcol align='left'>comments</ttcol>
        
        <c>msg_type</c>         <c>1</c>        <c>Occurs only in top level messages</c>
        <c>protected</c>        <c>2</c>        <c>Occurs in all structures</c>
        <c>unprotected</c>      <c>3</c>        <c>Occurs in all structures</c>
        <c>payload</c>          <c>4</c>        <c>Contains the content of the structure</c>
        <c>signatures</c>       <c>5</c>        <c>For COSE_Sign - array of signatures</c>
        <c>signature</c>        <c>6</c>        <c>For COSE_signature only</c>
        <c>ciphertext</c>       <c>4</c>        <c>TODO: Should we reuse the same as payload or not?</c>
        <c>recipients</c>       <c>9</c>        <c>For COSE_encrypt and COSE_mac</c>
        <c>tag</c>              <c>10</c>       <c>For COSE_mac only</c>
      </texttable>

      <t>
        The CDDL grammar that provides the label values is:
      </t>
      <figure><artwork type="CDDL"><![CDATA[
; message_labels
msg_type=1
protected=2
unprotected=3
payload=4
signatures=5
signature=6
ciphertext=4
recipients=9
tag=10

]]></artwork></figure>
      -->
      
    </section>

    <section anchor="header-parameters" title="Header Parameters">

      <t>
        The structure of COSE has been designed to have two buckets of information that are not considered to be part of the payload itself, but are used for holding information about content, algorithms, keys, or evaluation hints for the  processing of the layer.
        These two buckets are available for use in all of the structures in this document except for keys.
        While these buckets can be present, they may not all be usable in all instances.
        For example, while the protected bucket is defined as part of recipient structures, most of the algorithms that are used for recipients do not provide the necessary functionality to provide the needed protection and thus the bucket should not be used.
      </t>

      <t>
        Both buckets are implemented as CBOR maps.
        The map key is a 'label' (<xref target="label"/>).
        The value portion is dependent on the definition for the label.
        Both maps use the same set of label/value pairs. 
        The integer and string values for labels has been divided into several sections with a standard range, a private range, and a range that is dependent on the algorithm selected.
        The defined labels can be found in the 'COSE Header Parameters' IANA registry (<xref target="cose-header-key-table"/>).
      </t>

      <t>
        Two buckets are provided for each layer:

        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText='protected'>
            contains parameters about the current layer that are to be cryptographically protected.
            This bucket MUST be empty if it is not going to be included in a cryptographic computation.
            This bucket is encoded in the message as a binary object.
            This value is obtained by CBOR encoding the protected map and wrapping it in a bstr object.
            Senders SHOULD encode an empty protected map as a zero length binary object (it is shorter).
            Recipients MUST accept both a zero length binary value and a zero length map encoded in the binary value.
            The wrapping allows for the encoding of the protected map to be transported with a greater chance that it will not be altered in transit.
            (Badly behaved intermediates could decode and re-encode, but this will result in a failure to verify unless the re-encoded byte string is identical to the decoded byte string.)
            This finesses the problem of all parties needing to be able to do a common canonical encoding.
          </t>
          
          <t hangText='unprotected'>
            contains parameters about the current layer that are not cryptographically protected.
          </t>
        </list>

        Only parameters that deal with the current layer are to be placed at that layer.
        As an example of this, the parameter 'content type' describes the content of the message being carried in the message.
        As such this parameter is placed only the the content layer and is not placed in the recipient or signature layers.
        In principle, one should be able to process any given layer without reference to any other layer.
        (The only data that should need to cross layers is the cryptographic key.)
      </t>

      <t>
        The buckets are present in all of the security objects defined in this document.
        The fields in order are the 'protected' bucket (as a CBOR 'bstr' type) and then the 'unprotected' bucket (as a CBOR 'map' type).
        The presence of both buckets is required.
        The parameters that go into the buckets come from the IANA "COSE Header Parameters" (<xref target="cose-header-key-table"/>).
        Some common parameters are defined in the next section, but a number of parameters are defined throughout this document.
      </t>

      <!-- RFC EDITOR - Please make sure the following paragraphs have been removed. -->

      <t>
        Text from here to start of next section to be removed
        <cref source="JLS">
          A completest version of this grammar would list the options available in the protected and unprotected headers.
          Do we want to head that direction?
        </cref>
      </t>

      <figure><artwork type="CDDL"><![CDATA[
header_map = {+ label => any }

Headers = (
    protected : bstr,                  ; Contains a header_map
    unprotected : header_map
)
]]></artwork></figure>

      <section anchor="cose-headers" title="Common COSE Headers Parameters">
        <t>
          This section defines a set of common header parameters.
          A summary of those parameters can be found in <xref target="Header-Table"/>.
          This table should be consulted to determine the value of label used as well as the type of the value.
        </t>

        <t>
          The set of header parameters defined in this section are:
        </t>

        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText='alg'>
              This parameter is used to indicate the algorithm used for the security processing.
              This parameter MUST be present at each level of a signed, encrypted or authenticated message.
              The value is taken from the 'COSE Algorithm Registry' (see <xref target="cose-algorithm-registry"/>).
            </t>
            
            <t hangText='crit'>
              This parameter is used to ensure that applications will take appropriate action based on the values found.
              The parameter is used to indicate which protected header labels an application that is processing a message is required to understand.
              The value is an array of COSE Header Labels.
              When present, this parameter MUST be placed in the protected header bucket.
              <vspace/>
              <list style="symbols">
                <t>Integer labels in the range of 0 to 10 SHOULD be omitted.</t>
                
                <t>
                  Integer labels in the range -1 to -255 can be omitted as they are algorithm dependent.
                  If an application can correctly process an algorithm, it can be assumed that it will correctly process all of the parameters associated with that algorithm.
                  (The algorithm range is -1 to -65536, it is assumed that the higher end will deal with more optional algorithm specific items.)
                </t>
              </list>
              The header parameter values indicated by 'crit' can be processed by either the security library code or by an application using a security library, the only requirement is that the parameter is processed.
              If the 'crit' value list includes a value for which the parameter is not in the protected bucket, this is a fatal error in processing the message.
            </t>
            
            <t hangText='content type'>
              This parameter is used to indicate the content type of the data in the payload or ciphertext fields.
              Integers are from the 'CoAP Content-Formats' IANA registry table.
              Strings are from the IANA 'Media Types' registry.
              Applications SHOULD provide this parameter if the content structure is potentially ambiguous.
            </t>
            
            <t hangText='kid'>
              This parameter one of the ways that can be used to find the key to be used.
              The value of this parameter is matched against the 'kid' member in a COSE_Key structure.
              Applications MUST NOT assume that 'kid' values are unique.
              There may be more than one key with the same 'kid' value, it may be required that all of the keys need to be checked to find the correct one.
              The internal structure of 'kid' values is not defined and generally cannot be relied on by applications.
              Key identifier values are hints about which key to use, they are not directly a security critical field, for this reason they can be placed in the unprotected headers bucket.
            </t>

            <t hangText='nonce'>
              This parameter holds either a nonce or Initialization Vector value.
              The value can be used either as a counter value for a protocol or as an IV for an algorithm.
            </t>

            <t hangText='counter signature'>
              This parameter holds a counter signature value.
              Counter signatures provide a method of having a second party sign some data, the counter signature can occur as an unprotected attribute in any of the following structures: COSE_Sign, COSE_signature, COSE_enveloped, COSE_recipient, COSE_encryptedData, COSE_mac.
              These structures all have the same basic structure so that a consistent calculation of the counter signature can be computed.
              Details on computing counter signatures are found in <xref target="counter_signature"/>.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>


      <texttable anchor="Header-Table" title="Common Header Parameters">
        <ttcol align='left'>name</ttcol>
        <ttcol align='left'>label</ttcol>
        <ttcol align='left'>value type</ttcol>
        <ttcol align='left'>value registry</ttcol>
        <ttcol align='left'>description</ttcol>
        
        <c>alg</c>        <c>1</c>        <c>int / tstr</c>        <c>COSE Algorithm Registry</c>       <c>Integers are taken from table --POINT TO REGISTRY--</c>
        <c>crit</c>       <c>2</c>        <c>[+ label]</c>         <c>COSE Header Label Registry</c>    <c>integer values are from  -- POINT TO REGISTRY --</c>
        <c>content type</c> <c>3</c>        <c>tstr / int</c>        <c>CoAP Content-Formats or Media Types registry</c>          <c>Value is either a Media Type or an integer from the CoAP Content Format registry</c>
        <c>kid</c>        <c>4</c>        <c>bstr</c>              <c></c>                              <c>key identifier</c>
        <c>nonce</c>      <c>5</c>        <c>bstr</c>              <c></c>                              <c>Nonce or Initialization Vector (IV)</c>
        <c>counter signature</c> <c>6</c> <c>COSE_signature</c>    <c></c>                              <c>CBOR encoded signature structure</c>
      </texttable>

      <t>
        OPEN ISSUES:
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>
            I am currently torn on the question "Should epk and iv/nonce be algorithm specific or generic headers?"
            They are really specific to an algorithm and can potentially be defined in different ways for different algorithms.
            As an example, it would make sense to defined nonce for CCM and GCM modes that can have the leading zero bytes stripped, while for other algorithms this might be undesirable.
          </t>
          <t>
            We might want to define some additional items.  What are they?  A possible example would be a sequence number as this might be common.  On the other hand, this is the type of things that is frequently used as the nonce in some places and thus should not be used in the same way.  Other items might be challenge/response fields for freshness as these are likely to be common.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      </section>
    </section>

    
    <section anchor="signing-structure" title="Signing Structure">

      <t>
        The signature structure allows for one or more signatures to be applied to a message payload.
        There are provisions for parameters about the content and parameters about the signature to be carried along with the signature itself.
        These parameters may be authenticated by the signature, or just present.
        Examples of parameters about the content would be the type of content, when the content was created, and who created the content.
        <cref source="Hannes">
          Ensure that the list of examples only includes items which are implemented in this specification.
          Check the other places where such lists occur and ensure that they also follow this rule.
        </cref>
        Examples of parameters about the signature would be the algorithm and key used to create the signature, when the signature was created, and counter-signatures.
      </t>

      <t>
        When more than one signature is present, the successful validation of one signature associated with a given signer is usually treated as a successful signature by that signer.
        However, there are some application environments where other rules are needed.
        An application that employs a rule other than one valid signature for each signer must specify those rules.
        Also, where simple matching of the signer identifier is not sufficient to determine whether the signatures were generated by the same signer, the application specification must describe how to determine which signatures were generated by the same signer.
        Support of different communities of recipients is the primary reason that signers choose to include more than one signature.
        For example, the COSE_Sign structure might include signatures generated with the RSA signature algorithm and with the Elliptic Curve Digital Signature Algorithm (ECDSA) signature algorithm.
        This allows recipients to verify the signature associated with one algorithm or the other.
        (The original source of this text is <xref target="RFC5652"/>.)
        <!-- RFC Editor: This is not a direct quote from RFC 5652, but the basic text has come from there.  I want to acknowledge the original source of the quote but am not sure what is the correct way to go about this.-->
        More detailed information on multiple signature evaluation can be found in <xref target="RFC5752"/>.
      </t>

      <t>
        The COSE_Sign structure is a CBOR array.
        The fields of the array in order are:
      </t>

      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <!--
          <t hangText='msg_type'>
            identifies this as providing the signed security service.
            The value MUST be msg_type_signed (1).
            </t>
          -->
          
          <t hangText='protected'>
            is described in <xref target="header-parameters"/>.
          </t>
          
          <t hangText='unprotected'>
            is described in <xref target="header-parameters"/>.
          </t>
          
          <t hangText='payload'>
            contains the serialized content to be signed.
            If the payload is not present in the message, the application is required to supply the payload separately.
            The payload is wrapped in a bstr to ensure that it is transported without changes.
            If the payload is transported separately, then a nil CBOR object is placed in this location and it is the responsibility of the application to ensure that it will be transported without changes.
          </t>
          
          <t hangText='signatures'>
            is an array of signature items.
            Each of these items uses the COSE_signature structure for its representation.
          </t>
          
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>
        The COSE_signature structure is a CBOR array.
        The fields of the array in order are:
      </t>

      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText='protected'>
            is described in <xref target="header-parameters"/>.
          </t>
          
          <t hangText='unprotected'>
            is described in <xref target="header-parameters"/>.
          </t>
          
          <t hangText='signature'>
            contains the computed signature value.
            The type of the field is a bstr.
          </t>
          
        </list>
      </t>

      <!-- RFC EDITOR - Please make sure the following paragraphs have been removed. -->

      <t>
        Text from here to start of next section to be removed
      </t>


      <figure><artwork type="CDDL"><![CDATA[

COSE_Sign_Tagged = #6.999(COSE_Sign) ; Replace 999 with TBD1
      
COSE_Sign = [
    Headers,
    payload : bstr / nil,
    signatures : [+ COSE_signature]
]

COSE_signature =  [
    Headers,      
    signature : bstr
]
]]></artwork></figure>


      <section title="Externally Supplied Data" anchor="Extern_AAD">
        <t>
          One of the features that we supply in the COSE document is the ability for applications to provide additional data to be authenticated as part of the security, but that is not carried as part of the COSE object.
          The primary reason for supporting this can be seen by looking at the CoAP message struture <xref target="RFC7252"/> where the facility exists for options to be carried before the payload.
          An example of data that can be placed in this location would be transaction ids and nonces to check for replay protection.
          If the data is in the options section, then it is available for routers to help in performing the replay detection and prevention.
          However, it may also be desired to protect these values so that they cannot be modified in transit.
          This is the purpose of the externally supplied data field.
        </t>

        <t>
          This document describes the process for using a byte array of externally supplied authenticated data, however the method of constructing the byte array is a function of the application.
          Applications which use this feature need to define how the externally supplied authenticated data is to be constructed.
          Such a construction needs to take into account the following issues:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              If multiple items are included, care needs to be taken that data cannot bleed between the items.
              This is usually addressed by making fields fixed width and/or encoding the length of the field.
              Using options from CoAP as an example, these fields use a TLV structure so they can be concatenated without any problems.
            </t>
            <t>
              If multiple items are included, a defined order for the items needs to be defined.
              Using options from CoAP as an example, an application could state that the fields are to be ordered by the option number.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>


      <section title="Signing and Verification Process">

        <t>
          In order to create a signature, a consistent byte stream is needed in order to process.
          This document uses a CBOR array to construct the byte stream to be processed.
          The fields of the array in order are:
          <list style="numbers">
            <t>
              The body protected attributes.
              This is a bstr type containing the protected attributes of the body.
            </t>

            <t>
              The signature protected attributes.
              This is a bstr type containing the protected attributes of the signature.
            </t>

            <t>
              The external protected attributes.
              This is a bstr type containing the protected attributes external to the COSE_Signature structure.
            </t>

            <t>
              The payload to be signed.
              The payload is encoded in a bstr.
              The payload is placed here independent of how it is transported.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>
          How to compute a signature:

          <list style="numbers">
            <t>
              Create a CBOR array and populate it with the appropriate fields. 
              For body_protected and sign_protected, if the fields are not present in their corresponding maps, an bstr of length zero is used.
            </t>

            <t>
              If the application has supplied external additional authenticated data to be included in the computation, then it is placed in the third field.
              If no data was supplied, then a zero length binary value is used.
            </t>

            <t>
              Create the value ToBeSigned by encoding the Sig_structure to a byte string.
            </t>

            <t>
              Call the signature creation algorithm passing in K (the key to sign with), alg (the algorithm to sign with) and ToBeSigned (the value to sign).
            </t>

            <t>
              Place the resulting signature value in the 'signature' field of the map.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>
          How to verify a signature:

          <list style="numbers">
            <t>
              Create a Sig_structure object and populate it with the appropriate fields. 
              For body_protected and sign_protected, if the fields are not present in their corresponding maps, an bstr of length zero is used.
            </t>
            
            <t>
              If the application has supplied external additional authenticated data to be included in the computation, then it is placed in the third field.
              If no data was supplied, then a zero length binary value is used.
            </t>

            <t>
              Create the value ToBeSigned by encoding the Sig_structure to a byte string.
            </t>
            
            <t>
              Call the signature verification algorithm passing in K (the key to verify with), alg (the algorithm to sign with), ToBeSigned (the value to sign), and sig (the signature to be verified).
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>
          In addition to performing the signature verification, one must also perform the appropriate checks to ensure that the key is correctly paired with the signing identity and that the appropriate authorization is done.
        </t>

        <!-- RFC EDITOR - Please make sure the following paragraphs have been removed. -->

        <t>
          Text from here to start of next section to be removed
        </t>

        <t>
          The COSE structure used to create the byte stream to be signed uses the following CDDL grammar structure:
        </t>

        <figure><artwork type="CDDL"><![CDATA[
Sig_structure = [
    body_protected: bstr,
    sign_protected: bstr,
    external_aad: bstr,
    payload: bstr
]
]]></artwork></figure>

      </section>

      <section anchor="counter_signature" title="Computing Counter Signatures">
        <t>
          Counter signatures provide a method of having a different signature occur on some piece of content.
          This is normally used to provide a signature on a signature allowing for a proof that a signature existed at a given time.
          In this document we allow for counter signatures to exist in a greater number of environments.
          A counter signature can exist, for example, on a COSE_encyptedData object and allow for a signature to be present on the encrypted content of a message.
        </t>

        <t>
          The creation and validation of counter signatures over the different items relies on the fact that the structure all of our objects have the same structure.
          The first element may be a message type, this is followed by a set of protected attributes, a set of unprotected attributes and a body in that order.
          This means that the Sig_structure can be used for in a uniform manner to get the byte stream for processing a signature.
          If the counter signature is going to be computed over a COSE_encryptedData structure, the body_protected and payload items can be mapped into the Sig_structure in the same manner as from the COSE_Sign structure.
        </t>

        <t>
          While one can create a counter signature for a COSE_Sign structure, there is not much of a point to doing so.  It is equivalent to create a new COSE_signature structure and placing it in the signatures array.  It is strongly suggested that it not be done, but it is not banned.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="encryption-object" title="Encryption objects">
      <t>
        COSE supports two different encryption structures.
        OOSE_enveloped is used when the key needs to be explicilty identified.
        This structure supports the use of recipient structures to allow for random content encryption keys to be used..
        COSE_encrypted is used when the a recipient structure is not needed because the key to be used is known implicitly.
      </t>

      <section title="Enveloped COSE structure">

      <t>
        The enveloped structure allows for one or more recipients of a message.
        There are provisions for parameters about the content and parameters about the recipient information to be carried in the message.
        The parameters associated with the content can be authenticated by the content encryption algorithm.
        The parameters associated with the recipient can be authenticated by the recipient algorithm (when the algorithm supports it).
        Examples of parameters about the content are the type of the content, when the content was created, and the content encryption algorithm.
        Examples of parameters about the recipient are the recipients key identifier, the recipient encryption algorithm.
      </t>
      
      <t>
        In COSE, the same techniques and structures for encrypting both the plain text and the keys used to protect the text.
        This is different from the approach used by both <xref target="RFC5652"/> and <xref target="RFC7516"/> where different structures are used for the content layer and for the recipient layer.
      </t>

      <t>
        The COSE_encrypt structure is a CBOR array.
        The fields of the array in order are:

        <list style="hanging">
          <!--
          <t hangText='msg_type'>
            identifies this as providing the encrypted security service.
            The value MUST be msg_type_encrypted (2).
          </t>
          -->
          
          <t hangText='protected'>
            is described in <xref target="header-parameters"/>.
          </t>
          
          <t hangText='unprotected'>
            is described in <xref target="header-parameters"/>.
          </t>
          
          <t hangText='ciphertext'>
            contains the encrypted plain text encoded as a bstr.
            If the ciphertext is to be transported independently of the control information about the encryption process (i.e. detached content) then the field is encoded as a null object.
          </t>
          
          <t hangText='recipients'>
            contains an array of recipient information structures.
            The type for the recipient information structure is a COSE_recipient.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>
        The COSE_recipient structure is a CBOR array.
        The fields of the array in order are:

        <list style="hanging">

          <t hangText='protected'>
            is described in <xref target="header-parameters"/>.
          </t>
          
          <t hangText='unprotected'>
            is described in <xref target="header-parameters"/>.
          </t>
          
          <t hangText='ciphertext'>
            contains the encrypted key encoded as a bstr.
            If there is not an encrypted key, then this field is encoded as a nil type.
          </t>
          
          <t hangText='recipients'>
            contains an array of recipient information structures.
            The type for the recipient information structure is a COSE_recipient.
            If there are no recipient information structures, this element is absent.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <!-- RFC EDITOR - Please make sure the following paragraphs have been removed. -->

      <t>
        Text from here to start of next section to be removed
      </t>

      <figure><artwork type="CDDL"><![CDATA[

COSE_Enveloped_Tagged = #6.998(COSE_enveloped)          ; Replace 998 with TBD2
      
COSE_enveloped = [
    COSE_encrypt_fields
    recipients: [+COSE_recipient]
]

COSE_encrypt_fields = (
    Headers,
    ciphertext: bstr / nil,
)

COSE_recipient = [    
    COSE_encrypt_fields
    ? recipients: [+COSE_recipient]
]
]]></artwork></figure>

      <section anchor="key-management-methods" title="Recipient Algorithm Classes">
        <t>
          A typical encrypted message consists of an encrypted content and an encrypted CEK for one or more recipients.
          The content-encryption key is encrypted for each recipient, using a key specific to that recipient.
          The details of this encryption depends on which class the recipient algorithm falls into.
          Specific details on each of the classes can be found in <xref target="key-management-algs"/>.
          A short summary of the six recipient algorithm classes is:
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="none:"> The CEK is the same as as the identified previously distributed symmetric key or derived from a previously distributed secret.</t>
            <t hangText="symmetric key-encryption keys:"> The CEK is encrypted using a previously distributed symmetric key-encryption key.</t>
            <t hangText="key agreement:"> the recipient's public key and a sender's private key are used to generate a pairwise secret, a KDF is applied to derive a key, and then the CEK is either the derived key or encrypted by the derived key.</t>
            <t hangText="key transport:"> the CEK is encrypted in the recipient's public key</t>
            <t hangText="passwords:"> the CEK is encrypted in a key-encryption key that is derived from a password.</t>
          </list>
        </t>

      </section>

    </section>

    <section title="Encrypted COSE structure">
      <t>
        The encrypted structure does not have the ability to specify recipients of the message.
        The structure assumes that the recipient of the object will already know the identity of the key to be used in order to decrypt the message.
        If a key needs to be identified to the recipient, the enveloped structure is used.
      </t>

      <t>
        The CDDL grammar structure for encrypted data is:
      </t>

      <figure><artwork type="CDDL"><![CDATA[
COSE_EncryptedData_Tagged = #6.997(COSE_encryptData)     ; Replace 997 with TBD3
      
COSE_encryptData = [
    COSE_encrypt_fields
]
]]></artwork></figure>

      <t>
        The COSE_encryptedData structure is a CBOR array.
        The fields of the array in order are:

        <list style="hanging">
          <!--
          <t hangText='msg_type'>
            identifies this as providing the encrypted data security service.
            This value MUST be mg_type_encrypted (4).
            </t>
          -->
          <t hangText='protected'> is described in <xref target="header-parameters"/>.</t>
          <t hangText='unprotected'> is described in <xref target="header-parameters"/>.</t>
          <t hangText='ciphertext'>
            contains the encrypted plain text.
            If the ciphertext is to be transported independently of the control information about the encryption process (i.e. detached content) then the field is encoded as a null object.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

      
      <section anchor="encryption-algorithm-for-aead-algorithms" title="Encryption Algorithm for AEAD algorithms">

        <t>
          The encryption algorithm for AEAD algorithms is fairly simple.
          
          In order to get a consistent encoding of the data to be authenticated, the Enc_structure is used to have canonical form of the AAD.
        </t>

        <t>
          <list style="numbers">
            <t>
              Copy the protected header field from the message to be sent.
            </t>

            <t>
              If the application has supplied external additional authenticated data to be included in the computation, then it is placed in the 'external_aad' field.
              If no data was supplied, then a zero length binary value is used.
              (See <xref target="Extern_AAD"/> for application guidance on constructing this field.)
            </t>

            <t>
              Encode the Enc_structure using a CBOR Canonical encoding <xref target="CBOR-Canonical"/> to get the AAD value.
            </t>

            <t>
              Determine the encryption key.
              This step is dependent on the class of recipient algorithm being used.
              For:

              <list style="hanging">
                <t hangText="No Recipients:">
                  The key to be used is determined by the algorithm and key at the current level.
                </t>
                <t hangText="Direct and Direct Key Agreement:">
                  The key is determined by the key and algorithm in the recipient structure.
                  The encryption algorithm and size of the key to be used are inputs into the KDF used for the recipient.
                  (For direct, the KDF can be thought of as the identity operation.)
                </t>
                <t hangText="Other:">
                  The key is randomly generated.
                </t>
              </list>
            </t>
            
            <t>
              Call the encryption algorithm with K (the encryption key to use), P (the plain text) and AAD (the additional authenticated data).
              Place the returned cipher text into the 'ciphertext' field of the structure.
            </t>

            <t>
              For recipients of the message, recursively perform the encryption algorithm for that recipient using the encryption key as the plain text.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <!-- RFC EDITOR - Please make sure the following paragraphs have been removed. -->

        <t>
          Text from here to start of next section to be removed
        </t>

        <figure><artwork type="CDDL"><![CDATA[
Enc_structure = [
    protected: bstr,
    external_aad: bstr
]

]]></artwork></figure>

      </section>
      <section anchor="encryption-algorithm-for-ae-algorithms" title="Encryption algorithm for AE algorithms">

        <t>
          <list style="numbers">
            <t>
              Verify that the 'protected' field is absent.
            </t>
            <t>
              Verify that there was no external additional authenticated data supplied for this operation.
            </t>
            <t>
              Determine the encryption key.
              This step is dependent on the class of recipient algorithm being used.
              For:

              <list style="hanging">
                <t hangText="No Recipients:">
                  The key to be used is determined by the algorithm and key at the current level.
                </t>
                <t hangText="Direct and Direct Key Agreement:">
                  The key is determined by the key and algorithm in the recipient structure.
                  The encryption algorithm and size of the key to be used are inputs into the KDF used for the recipient.
                  (For direct, the KDF can be thought of as the identity operation.)
                </t>
                <t hangText="Other:">
                  The key is randomly generated.
                </t>
              </list>
            </t>
            
            <t>
              Call the encryption algorithm with K (the encryption key to use) and the P (the plain text).
              Place the returned cipher text into the 'ciphertext' field of the structure.
            </t>

            <t>
              For recipients of the message, recursively perform the encryption algorithm for that recipient using the encryption key as the plain text.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>

      </section>
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="mac-objects" title="MAC objects">

      <t>
        In this section we describe the structure and methods to be used when doing MAC authentication in COSE. 
        This document allows for the use of all of the same classes of recipient algorithms as are allowed for encryption.
      </t>

      <t>
        When using MAC operations, there are two modes in which it can be used. 
        The first is just a check that the content has not been changed since the MAC was computed. 
        Any class of recipient algorithm can be used for this purpose. 
        The second mode is to both check that the content has not been changed since the MAC was computed, and to use recipient algorithm to verify who sent it.
        The classes of recipient algorithms that support this are those that use a pre-shared secret or do static-static key agreement (without the key wrap step).
        In both of these cases the entity MACing the message can be validated by a key binding. 
        (The binding of identity assumes that there are only two parties involved and you did not send the message yourself.)
      </t>

      <t>
        The COSE_Mac structure is a CBOR array.
        The fields of the array in order are:

        <list style="hanging">
          <!--
          <t hangText='msg_type'>
            identifies this as providing the encrypted security service.
            The value MUST be msg_type_mac (3).
          </t>
          -->

          <t hangText='protected'>
            is described in <xref target="header-parameters"/>.
          </t>

          <t hangText='unprotected'>
            is described in <xref target="header-parameters"/>.
          </t>

          <t hangText='payload'>
            contains the serialized content to be MACed.
            If the payload is not present in the message, the application is required to supply the payload separately.
            The payload is wrapped in a bstr to ensure that it is transported without changes.
            If the payload is transported separately, then a null CBOR object is placed in this location and it is the responsibility of the application to ensure that it will be transported without changes.
          </t>

          <t hangText='tag'>
            contains the MAC value.
          </t>

          <t hangText='recipients'>
            contains the recipient information.  
            See the description under COSE_Encryption for more info.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <!-- RFC EDITOR - Please make sure the following paragraphs have been removed. -->

      <t>
        Text from here to start of next section to be removed
      </t>

      <figure><artwork type="CDDL"><![CDATA[
COSE_Mac_Tagged = #6.996(COSE_Mac)              ; Repalce 996 with TBD4
      
COSE_Mac = [
   Headers,
   payload: bstr / nil,
   tag: bstr,
   recipients: [+COSE_recipient]
]

]]></artwork></figure>

        <section title="How to compute a MAC">

          <t>
            How to compute a MAC:
          </t>

          <t>
            <list style="numbers">
              <t>
                Create a MAC_structure and copy the protected and payload fields from the COSE_Mac structure.
              </t>
              <t>
                If the application has supplied external authenticated data, encode it as a binary value and place in the MAC_structure.
                If there is no external authenticated data, then use a zero length 'bstr'.
                (See <xref target="Extern_AAD"/> for application guidance on constructing this field.)
              </t>
              <t>
                Encode the MAC_structure using a canonical CBOR encoder.  The resulting bytes is the value to compute the MAC on.
              </t>
              <t>
                Compute the MAC and place the result in the 'tag' field of the COSE_Mac structure.
              </t>
              <t>
                Encrypt and encode the MAC key for each recipient of the message.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>

          <!-- RFC EDITOR - Please make sure the following paragraphs have been removed. -->

          <t>
            Text from here to start of next section to be removed
          </t>

          <figure><artwork type="CDDL"><![CDATA[
MAC_structure = [
     protected: bstr,
     external_aad: bstr,
     payload: bstr
]
]]></artwork></figure>

        </section>
      </section>
    <section anchor="key-structure" title="Key Structure">

      <t>
        A COSE Key structure is built on a CBOR map object.
        The set of common parameters that can appear in a COSE Key can be found in the IANA registry 'COSE Key Common Parameter Registry' (<xref target="cose-key-map-registry"/>).
        Additional parameters defined for specific key types can be found in the IANA registry 'COSE Key Type Parameters' (<xref target="cose-key-parameter-registry"/>).
      </t>

      <t>
        A COSE Key Set uses a CBOR array object as it's underlying type.
        The values of the array elements are COSE Keys.
        A Key Set MUST have at least one element in the array.
        <cref source="JLS">
          Is there a reason to assign a CBOR tag to identify keys and/or key sets?
        </cref>
      </t>

      <t>
        The element “kty” is a required element in a COSE_Key map.
      </t>

      <!-- RFC EDITOR - Please make sure the following paragraphs have been removed. -->

      <t>
        Text from here to start of next section to be removed
      </t>

      <t>
        The CDDL grammar describing a COSE_Key and COSE_KeySet is:
        <cref source="JLS">
          We can really simplify the grammar for COSE_Key to be just the kty (the one required field) and the generic item.
          The reason to do this is that it makes things simpler.
          The reason not to do this says that we really need to add a lot more items so that a grammar check can be done that is more tightly enforced.
        </cref>
      </t>

      <figure><artwork type="CDDL"><![CDATA[
COSE_Key = {
    key_kty => tstr / int,
    ? key_ops => [+ (tstr / int) ],
    ? key_alg => tstr / int,
    ? key_kid => bstr,
    * label => values
}

COSE_KeySet = [+COSE_Key]
]]></artwork></figure>


    <section anchor="COSE_KEY_KEYS" title="COSE Key Common Parameters">

      <t>
        This document defines a set of common parameters for a COSE Key object.
        <xref target="table-key-labels"/> provides a summary of the parameters defined in this section.
        There are also a set of parameters that are defined for a specific key type.
        Key type specific parameters can be found in <xref target="Key-specific-labels"/>.
      </t>

      <texttable title="Key Map Labels" anchor="table-key-labels">
        <ttcol align='left'>name</ttcol>
        <ttcol align='left'>label</ttcol>
        <ttcol align='left'>CBOR type</ttcol>
        <ttcol align='left'>registry</ttcol>
        <ttcol align='left'>description</ttcol>
        
        <c>kty</c>        <c>1</c>        <c>tstr / int</c>  <c>COSE General Values</c>        <c>Identification of the key type</c>
        <c>key_ops</c>    <c>4</c>        <c>[* (tstr/int)]</c> <c></c>     <c>Restrict set of permissible operations</c>
        <c>alg</c>        <c>3</c>        <c>tstr / int</c>  <c>COSE Algorithm Values</c>        <c>Key usage restriction to this algorithm</c>
        <c>kid</c>        <c>2</c>        <c>bstr</c>        <c></c>        <c>Key Identification value - match to kid in message</c>
        <c>use</c>        <c>*</c>        <c>tstr</c>        <c></c>        <c>deprecated - don't use</c>
      </texttable>

      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="kty:">
            This parameter is used to identify the family of keys for this structure, and thus the set of key type specific parameters to be found.
            The set of values can be found in <xref target="table_key_types"/>.
            This parameter MUST be present in a key object.
            Implementations MUST verify that the key type is appropriate for the algorithm being processed.
            The key type MUST be included as part of a trust decision process.
          </t>
          
          <t hangText="alg:">
            This parameter is used to restrict the algorithms that are to be used with this key.
            If this parameter is present in the key structure, the application MUST verify that this algorithm matches the algorithm for which the key is being used.
            If the algorthms do not match, then this key object MUST NOT be used to perform the cryptographic operation.
            Note that the same key can be in a different key structure with a different or no algorithm specified, however this is considered to be a poor security practice.
          </t>
          
          <t hangText="kid:">
            This parameter is used to give an identifier for a key.
            The identifier is not structured and can be anything from a user provided string to a value computed on the public portion of the key.
            This field is intended for matching against a 'kid' parameter in a message in order to filter down the set of keys that need to be checked.
          </t>
          
          <t hangText="key_ops:">
            This parameter is defined to restrict the set of operations that a key is to be used for.
            The value of the field is an array of values from <xref target="table-key-ops"/>.
          </t>
          
        </list>
      </t>

      <texttable title="Key Operation Values" anchor="table-key-ops">
        <ttcol>name</ttcol>
        <ttcol>value</ttcol>
        <ttcol>description</ttcol>
        <c>sign</c>             <c>1</c>        <c>The key is used to create signatures.  Requires private key fields.</c>
        <c>verify</c>           <c>2</c>        <c>The key is used for verification of signatures.</c>
        <c>encrypt</c>          <c>3</c>        <c>The key is used for key transport encryption.</c>
        <c>decrypt</c>          <c>4</c>        <c>The key is used for key transport decryption.  Requires private key fields.</c>
        <c>wrap key</c>         <c>5</c>        <c>The key is used for key wrapping.</c>
        <c>unwrap key</c>       <c>6</c>        <c>The key is used for key unwrapping.  Requires private key fields.</c>
        <c>key agree</c>        <c>7</c>        <c>The key is used for key agreement.</c>
      </texttable>
      
      <!-- RFC EDITOR - Please make sure the following paragraphs have been removed. -->

      <t>
        Text from here to start of next section to be removed
      </t>

      <t>
        The following provides a CDDL fragment which duplicates the assignment labels from <xref target="table-key-labels"/> and <xref target="table-key-ops"/>.
      </t>
      
      <figure><artwork type="CDDL"><![CDATA[
;key_labels
key_kty=1
key_kid=2
key_alg=3
key_ops=4

;key_ops values
key_ops_sign=1
key_ops_verify=2
key_ops_encrypt=3
key_ops_decrypt=4
key_ops_wrap=5
key_ops_unwrap=6
key_ops_agree=7
]]></artwork></figure>

    </section>
      
    </section>


    <section title="Signature Algorithms">
      <t>
        There are two basic signature algorithm structures that can be used.
        The first is the common signature with appendix.
        In this structure, the message content is processed and a signature is produced, the signature is called the appendix.
        This is the message structure used by our common algorithms such as ECDSA and RSASSA-PSS.
        (In fact the SSA in RSASSA-PSS stands for Signature Scheme with Appendix.)
        The basic structure becomes:
      </t>
      <figure><artwork>
        <![CDATA[
signature = Sign(message content, key)

valid = Verification(message content, key, signature)
]]>
      </artwork></figure>
      
      <t>
        The second is a signature with message recovery.
        (An example of such an algorithm is <xref target="PVSig"/>.)
        In this structure, the message content is processed, but part of is included in the signature.
        Moving bytes of the message content into the signature allows for an effectively smaller signature, the signature size is still potentially large, but the message content is shrunk.
        This has implications for systems implementing these algoritms and for applications that use them.
        The first is that the message content is not fully available until after a signature has been validated.
        Until that point the part of the message contained inside of the signature is unrecoverable.
        The second is that the security analysis of the strength of the signature is very much based on the structure of the message content.
        Messages which are highly predictable require additional randomness to be supplied as part of the signature process, in the worst case it becomes the same as doing a signature with appendix.
        Thirdly, in the event that multple signatures are applied to a message, all of the signature algorithms are going to be required to consume the same number of bytes of message content.
      </t>

      <figure><artwork>
        <![CDATA[
signature, message sent = Sign(message content, key)

valid, message content = Verification(message sent, key, signature)
]]>
      </artwork></figure>

      <t>
        At this time, only signatures with appendixes are defined for use with COSE, however considerable interest has been expressed in using a signature with message recovery algorithm due to the effective size reduction that is possible.
        Implementations will need to keep this in mind for later possible integration.
      </t>
      
      <section title="ECDSA">
        <t>
          ECDSA <xref target="DSS"/> defines a signature algorithm using ECC.
        </t>

        <t>
          The ECDSA signature algorithm is parameterized with a hash function (h).
          In the event that the length of the hash function output is greater than group of the key, the left most bytes of the hash output are used.
        </t>

        <t>
          The algorithms defined in this document can be found in <xref target="table_ecdsa"/>.
        </t>
        
        <texttable title="ECDSA Algorithm Values" anchor="table_ecdsa">
          <ttcol align='left'>name</ttcol>
          <ttcol align='left'>value</ttcol>
          <ttcol align='left'>hash</ttcol>
          <ttcol align='left'>description</ttcol>
          <c>ES256</c>        <c>-7</c>       <c>SHA-256</c>   <c>ECDSA w/ SHA-256</c>
          <c>ES384</c>        <c>-8</c>       <c>SHA-384</c>   <c>ECDSA w/ SHA-384</c>
          <c>ES512</c>        <c>-9</c>       <c>SHA-512</c>   <c>ECDSA w/ SHA-512</c>
        </texttable>

        <t>
          This document defines ECDSA to work only with the curves P-256, P-384 and P-521.
          This document requires that the curves be encoded using the 'EC2' key type.
          Implementations need to check that the key type and curve are correct when creating and verifying a signature.
          Other documents can defined it to work with other curves and points in the future.
        </t>

        <t>
          In order to promote interoperability, it is suggested that SHA-256 be used only with curve P-256, SHA-384 be used only with curve P-384 and SHA-512 be used with curve P-521.
          This is aligned with the recommendation in Section 4 of <xref target="RFC5480"/>.
        </t>

        <t>
          The signature algorithm results in a pair of integers (R, S).
          These integers will be of the same order as length of the key used for the signature process.
          The signature is encoded by converting the integers into byte strings of the same length as the key size.
          The length is rounded up to the nearest byte and is left padded with zero bits to get to the correct length.
          The two integers are then concatenated together to form a byte string that is the resulting signature.
        </t>

        <t>
          Using the function defined in <xref target="RFC3447"/> the signature is:
          <vspace/>
          Signature = I2OSP(R, n) | I2OSP(S, n)
          <vspace/>
          where n = ceiling(key_length / 8)
        </t>

        <section title="Security Considerations">
          <t>
          The security strength of the signature is no greater than the minimum of the security strength associated with the bit length of the key and the security strength of the hash function.
        </t>

        <t>
          System which have poor random number generation can leak their keys by signing two different messages with the same value of 'k'.
          <xref target="RFC6979"/> provides a method to deal with this problem by making 'k' be deterministic based on the message content rather than randomly generated.
          Applications which specify ECDSA should evaluate the ability to get good random number generation and require this when it is not possible.
          Note: Use of this technique a good idea even when good random number generation exists.
          Doing so both reduces the possiblity of having the same value of 'k' in two signature operations, but allows for reproducable signature values which helps testing.
        </t>

        <t>
          There are two substitution that can theoretically be mounted against the ECDSA signature algorithm.
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              Changing the curve used to validate the signature:
              If one changes the curve used to validate the signature, then potentially one could have a two messages with the same signature each computed under a different curve.
              The only requirement on the new curve is that it's order be the same as the old one and it be acceptable to the client.
              An example would be to change from using the curve secp256r1 (aka P-256) to using secp256k1.
              (Both are 256 bit curves.)
              We current do not have any way to deal with this version of the attack except to restrict the overall set of curves that can be used.
            </t>

            <t>
              Change the hash function used to validate the signature:
              If one has either two different hash functions of the same length, or one can truncate a hash function down, then one could potentially find collisions between the hash functions rather than within a single hash function.
              (For example, truncating SHA-512 to 256 bits might collide with a SHA-256 bit hash value.)
              This attack can be mitigated by including the signature algorithm identifier in the data to be signed.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        </section>
        
      </section>

      <section title="RSASSA-PSS">
        <t>
          The RSASSA-PSS signature algorithm is defined in <xref target="RFC3447"/>.
        </t>

        <t>
          The RSASSA-PSS signature algorithm is parametized with a hash function (h), a mask generation function (mgf) and a salt length (sLen).
          For this specification, the mask generation function is fixed to be MGF1 as defined in <xref target="RFC3447"/>.
          It has been recommended that the same hash function be used for hashing the data as well as in the mask generation function, for this specification we following this recommendation.
          The salt length is the same length as the hash function output.
        </t>

        <t>
          Implementations need to check that the key type is 'RSA' when creating or verifying a signature.
        </t>

        <t>
          The algorithms defined in this document can be found in <xref target="table-rsa-algs"/>.
        </t>
        
        <texttable anchor="table-rsa-algs" title="RSASSA-PSS Algorithm Values">
          <ttcol align='left'>name</ttcol>
          <ttcol align='left'>value</ttcol>
          <ttcol>hash</ttcol>
          <ttcol>salt length</ttcol>
          <ttcol align='left'>description</ttcol>
          <c>PS256</c>        <c>-26</c>      <c>SHA-256</c>    <c>32</c>       <c>RSASSA-PSS w/ SHA-256</c>
          <c>PS384</c>        <c>-27</c>      <c>SHA-384</c>    <c>48</c>       <c>RSASSA-PSS w/ SHA-384</c>
          <c>PS512</c>        <c>-28</c>      <c>SHA-512</c>    <c>64</c>       <c>RSASSA-PSS w/ SHA-512</c>
        </texttable>

        <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="RSASSA-PSS-considerations">
          <t>
            In addition to needing to worry about keys that are too small to provide the required security,  there are issues with keys that are too large.
            Denial of service attacks have been mounted with overly large keys.
            This has the potential to consume resources with potentially bad keys.
            There are two reasonable ways to address this attack.
            First, a key should not be used for a cryptographic operation until it has been matched back to an authorized user.
            This approach means that no cryptography would be done except for authorized users.
            Second, applications can impose maximum as well as minimum length requirements on keys.
            This limits the resources consumed even if the matching is not performed until the cryptography has been done.
          </t>

          <t>
            There is a theoretical hash substitution attack that can be mounted against RSASSA-PSS.
            However, the requirement that the same hash function be used consistently for all operations is an effective mitigation against it.
            Unlike ECDSA, hash functions are not truncated so that the full hash value is always signed.
            The internal padding structure of RSASSA-PSS means that one needs to have multiple collisions between the two hash functions in order to be successful in producing a forgery based on changing the hash function.
            This is highly unlikely.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
      

    </section>

    <section title="Message Authentication (MAC) Algorithms">
      <t>
        Message Authentication Codes (MACs) provide data authentication and integrity protection.
        They provide either no or very limited data origination.
        (One cannot, for example, be used to prove the identity of the sender to a third party.)
      </t>

      <t>
        MACs are designed in the same basic structure as signature with appendix algorithms.
        The message content is processed and an authentication code is produced, the authentication code is frequently called a tag.
        The basic structure becomes:
      </t>
      <figure><artwork>
        <![CDATA[
tag = MAC_Create(message content, key)

valid = MAC_Verify(message content, key, tag)
]]>
      </artwork></figure>
      

      <t>
        MAC algorithms can be based on either a block cipher algorithm (i.e. AES-MAC) or a hash algorithm (i.e. HMAC).
        This document defines a MAC algorithm for each of these two constructions.
      </t>

      <section title="Hash-based Message Authentication Codes (HMAC)">
        <t>
          The Hash-base Message Authentication Code algorithm (HMAC) <xref target="RFC2104"/><xref target="RFC4231"/> was designed to deal with length extension attacks.
          The algorithm was also designed to allow for new hash algorithms to be directly plugged in without changes to the hash function.
          The HMAC design process has been vindicated as, while the security of hash algorithms such as MD5 has decreased over time, the security of HMAC combined with MD5 has not yet been shown to be compromised <xref target="RFC6151"/>.
        </t>

        <t>
          The HMAC algorithm is parameterized by an inner and outer padding, a hash function (h) and an authentication tag value length.
          For this specification, the inner and outer padding are fixed to the values set in <xref target="RFC2104"/>.
          The length of the authentication tag corresponds to the difficulty of producing a forgery.
          For use in constrained environments, we define a set of HMAC algorithms that are truncated.
          There are currently no known issues when truncating, however the security strength of the message tag is correspondingly reduced in strength.
          When truncating, the left most tag length bits are kept and transmitted.
        </t>

        <t>
          The algorithm defined in this document can be found in <xref target="table-hmac"/>.
        </t>
        
        <texttable title="HMAC Algorithm Values" anchor="table-hmac">
          <ttcol align='left'>name</ttcol>
          <ttcol align='left'>value</ttcol>
          <ttcol align='left'>Hash</ttcol>
          <ttcol align='left'>Length</ttcol>
          <ttcol align='left'>description</ttcol>
          <c>HMAC 256/64</c>         <c>*</c>        <c>SHA-256</c>    <c>64</c>        <c>HMAC w/ SHA-256 truncated to 64 bits</c>
          <c>HMAC 256/256</c>        <c>4</c>        <c>SHA-256</c>    <c>256</c>       <c>HMAC w/ SHA-256</c>
          <c>HMAC 384/384</c>        <c>5</c>        <c>SHA-384</c>    <c>384</c>       <c>HMAC w/ SHA-384</c>
          <c>HMAC 512/512</c>        <c>6</c>        <c>SHA-512</c>    <c>512</c>       <c>HMAC w/ SHA-512</c>
        </texttable>

        <t>
          Some recipient algorithms carry the key while others derive a key from secret data.
          For those algorithms which carry the key (i.e. RSA-OAEP and AES-KeyWrap), the size of the HMAC key SHOULD be the same size as the underlying hash function.
          For those algorithms which derive the key, the derived key MUST be the same size as the underlying hash function.
        </t>

        <t>
          If the key obtained from a key structure, the key type MUST be 'Symmetric'.
          Implementations creating and validating MAC values MUST validate that the key type, key length and algorithm are correct and appropriate for the entities involved.
        </t>

        <section title="Security Considerations">
          <t>
            HMAC has proved to be resistant even when used with weakening hash algorithms.
            The current best method appears to be a brute force attack on the key.
            This means that key size is going to be directly related to the security of an HMAC operation.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="AES Message Authentication Code (AES-CBC-MAC)">
        <t>
          AES-CBC-MAC is defined in <xref target="MAC"/>.
        </t>

        <t>
          AES-CBC-MAC is parameterized by the key length, the authentication tag length and the IV used.
          For all of these algorithms, the IV is fixed to all zeros.
          We provide an array of algorithms for various key lengths and tag lengths.
          The algorithms defined in this document are found in <xref target="table-aes-mac"/>.
        </t>
        

        <texttable title="AES-MAC Algorithm Values" anchor="table-aes-mac">
          <ttcol align='left'>name</ttcol>
          <ttcol align='left'>value</ttcol>
          <ttcol align='left'>key length</ttcol>
          <ttcol align='left'>tag length</ttcol>
          <ttcol align='left'>description</ttcol>
          <c>AES-MAC 128/64</c>         <c>*</c>        <c>128</c>      <c>64</c>       <c>AES-MAC 128 bit key, 64-bit tag</c>
          <c>AES-MAC 256/64</c>         <c>*</c>        <c>256</c>      <c>64</c>       <c>AES-MAC 256 bit key, 64-bit tag</c>
          <c>AES-MAC 128/128</c>        <c>*</c>        <c>128</c>      <c>128</c>      <c>AES-MAC 128 bit key, 128-bit tag</c>
          <c>AES-MAC 256/128</c>        <c>*</c>        <c>256</c>      <c>128</c>      <c>AES-MAC 256 bit key, 128-bit tag</c>
          
        </texttable>

        <t>
          Keys may be obtained either from a key structure or from a recipient structure.
          If the key obtained from a key structure, the key type MUST be 'Symmetric'.
          Implementations creating and validating MAC values MUST validate that the key type, key length and algorithm are correct and appropriate for the entities involved.
        </t>

        <section title="Security Considerations">
          <t>
            A number of attacks exist against CBC-MAC that need to be considered.
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                A single key must only be used for messages of a fixed and known length.
                If this is not the case, an attacker will be able to generated a message with a valid tag given two message, tag pairs.
                This can be addressed by using different keys for different length messages.
                (CMAC mode also addresses this issue.)
              </t>
              <t>
                If the same key is used for both encryption and authentication operations, using CBC modes an attacker can produce messages with a valid authentication code.
              </t>
              <t>
                If the IV can be modified, then messages can be forged.
                This is addressed by fixing the IV to all zeros.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
            
        </section>

      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Content Encryption Algorithms">
      <t>
        Content Encryption Algorithms provide data confidentialty for potentially large blocks of data using a symmetric key.
        They provide either no or very limited data origination.
        (One cannot, for example, be used to prove the identity of the sender to a third party.)
        The ability to provide data origination is linked to how the symmetric key is obtained.
      </t>

      <t>
        We restrict the set of legal content encryption algorithms to those which support authentication both of the content and additional data.
        The encryption process will generate some type of authentication value, but that value may be either explicit or implicit in terms of the algorithm definition.
        For simplicity sake, the authentication code will normally be defined as being appended to the cipher text stream.
        The basic structure becomes:
      </t>
      <figure><artwork>
        <![CDATA[
ciphertext = Encrypt(message content, key, additional data)

valid, message content = Decrypt(cipher text, key, additional data)
]]>
      </artwork></figure>

      <t>
        Most AEAD algorithms are logically defined as returning the message content only if the decryption is valid.
        Many but not all implementations will follow this convention.
        The message content MUST NOT be used if the decryption does not validate.
      </t>
      
      <section title="AES GCM">
        <t>
          The GCM mode is is a generic authenticated encryption block cipher mode defined in <xref target="AES-GCM"/>.
          The GCM mode is combined with the AES block encryption algorithm to define a an AEAD cipher.
        </t>

        <t>
          The GCM mode is parameterized with by the size of the authentication tag.
          The size of the authentication tag is limited to a small set of values.
          For this document however, the size of the authentication tag is fixed at 128-bits.
        </t>

        <t>
          The set of algorithms defined in this document are in <xref target="table-AES-GCM"/>.
        </t>
        
        <texttable title="Algorithm Value for AES-GCM" anchor="table-AES-GCM">
          <ttcol align='left'>name</ttcol>
          <ttcol align='left'>value</ttcol>
          <ttcol align='left'>description</ttcol>
          <c>A128GCM</c>        <c>1</c>        <c>AES-GCM mode w/ 128-bit key</c>
          <c>A192GCM</c>        <c>2</c>        <c>AES-GCM mode w/ 192-bit key</c>
          <c>A256GCM</c>        <c>3</c>        <c>AES-GCM mode w/ 256-bit key</c>
        </texttable>

        <t>
          Keys may be obtained either from a key structure or from a recipient structure.
          If the key obtained from a key structure, the key type MUST be 'Symmetric'.
          Implementations creating and validating MAC values MUST validate that the key type, key length and algorithm are correct and appropriate for the entities involved.
        </t>

        <section title="Security Considerations">
          <t>
            When using AES-CCM the following restrictions MUST be enforced:
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                The key and nonce pair MUST be unique for every message encrypted.
              </t>
              <t>
                The total amount of data encrypted MUST NOT exceed 2^39 − 256 bits .
                An explicit check is required only in environments where it is expected that it might be exceeded.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>

        </section>
      </section>
      
      <section title="AES CCM">
        <t>
          Counter with CBC-MAC (CCM) is a generic authentication encryption block cipher mode defined in <xref target="RFC3610"/>.
          The CCM mode is combined with the AES block encryption algorithm to define a commonly used content encryption algorithm used in constrainted devices.
        </t>

        <t>
          The CCM mode has two parameter choices.
          The first choice is M, the size of the authentication field.
          The choice of the value for M involves a trade-off between message expansion and the probably that an attacker can undetecably modify a message.
          
          The second choice is L, the size of the length field.
          This value requires a trade-off between the maximum message size and the size of the Nonce.
        </t>

        <t>
          It is unfortunate that the specification for CCM specified L and M as a count of bytes rather than a count of bits.
          This leads to possible misunderstandings where AES-CCM-8 is frequently used to refer to a version of CCM mode where the size of the authentication is 64-bits and not 8-bits.
          These values have traditionally been specified as bit counts rather than byte counts.
          This document will follow the tradition of using bit counts so that it is easier to compare the different algorithms presented in this document.
        </t>

        <t>
          We define a matrix of algorithms in this document over the values of L and M.
          Constrained devices are usually operating in situations where they use short messages and want to avoid doing recipient specific cryptographic operations.
          This favors smaller values of M and larger values of L.
          Less constrained devices do will want to be able to user larger messages and are more willing to generate new keys for every operation.
          This favors larger values of M and smaller values of L.
          (The use of a large nonce means that random generation of both the key and the nonce will decrease the chances of repeating the pair on two different messages.)
        </t>

        <t>
          The following values are used for L:
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="16-bits (2)">
              limits messages to 2^16 bytes (64Kbyte) in length.
              This sufficently long for messages in the constrainted world.
              The nonce length is 13 bytes allowing for 2^(13*8) possible values of the nonce without repeating.
            </t>
            <t hangText="64-bits (8)"> 
              limits messages to 2^64 byes in length.
              The nonce length is 7 bytes allowing for 2^56 possible values of the nonce without repeating.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>
          The following values are used for M:
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="64-bits (8)">
              produces a 64-bit authentication tag.
              This implies that there is a 1 in 2^64 chance that an modified message will authenticate.
            </t>
            <t hangText="128-bits (16)">
              produces a 128-bit authentication tag.
              This implies that there is a 1 in 2^128 chance that an modified message will authenticate.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        
        <texttable anchor="table-AES-CCM" title="Algorithm Values for AES-CCM">
          <ttcol align='left'>name</ttcol>
          <ttcol align='left'>value</ttcol>
          <ttcol align='left'>L</ttcol>
          <ttcol align='left'>M</ttcol>
          <ttcol align='left'>k</ttcol>
          <ttcol align='left'>description</ttcol>
          <c>AES-CCM-16-64-128</c>        <c>10</c>    <c>16</c>       <c>64</c>       <c>128</c>      <c>AES-CCM mode 128-bit key, 64-bit tag, 13-byte nonce</c>
          <c>AES-CCM-16-64-256</c>        <c>11</c>    <c>16</c>       <c>64</c>       <c>256</c>      <c>AES-CCM mode 256-bit key, 64-bit tag, 13-byte nonce</c>
          <c>AES-CCM-64-64-128</c>        <c>30</c>    <c>64</c>       <c>64</c>       <c>128</c>      <c>AES-CCM mode 128-bit key, 64-bit tag, 7-byte nonce</c>
          <c>AES-CCM-64-64-256</c>        <c>31</c>    <c>64</c>       <c>64</c>       <c>256</c>      <c>AES-CCM mode 256-bit key, 64-bit tag, 7-byte nonce</c>
          <c>AES-CCM-16-128-128</c>       <c>12</c>    <c>16</c>       <c>128</c>      <c>128</c>      <c>AES-CCM mode 128-bit key, 128-bit tag, 13-byte nonce</c>
          <c>AES-CCM-16-128-256</c>       <c>13</c>    <c>16</c>       <c>128</c>      <c>256</c>      <c>AES-CCM mode 256-bit key, 128-bit tag, 13-byte nonce</c>
          <c>AES-CCM-64-128-128</c>       <c>32</c>    <c>64</c>       <c>128</c>      <c>128</c>      <c>AES-CCM mode 128-bit key, 128-bit tag, 7-byte nonce</c>
          <c>AES-CCM-64-128-256</c>       <c>33</c>    <c>64</c>       <c>128</c>      <c>256</c>      <c>AES-CCM mode 256-bit key, 128-bit tag, 7-byte nonce</c>
        </texttable>

        <t>
          Keys may be obtained either from a key structure or from a recipient structure.
          If the key obtained from a key structure, the key type MUST be 'Symmetric'.
          Implementations creating and validating MAC values MUST validate that the key type, key length and algorithm are correct and appropriate for the entities involved.
        </t>

        <section title="Security Considerations">
          <t>
            When using AES-CCM the following restrictions MUST be enforced:
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                The key and nonce pair MUST be unique for every message encrypted.
              </t>
              <t>
                The total number of times the AES block cipher is used MUST NOT exceed 2^61 operations.
                This limitation is the sum of times the block cipher is used in computing the MAC value and in performing stream encryption operations.
                An explicit check is required only in environments where it is expected that it might be exceeded.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>

          <t>
            <xref target="RFC3610"/> additionally calls out one other consideration of note.
            It is possible to do a pre-computation attack against the algorithm in cases where the portions encryption content is highly predictable.
            This reduces the security of the key size by half.
            Ways to deal with this attack include adding a random portion to the nonce value and/or increasing the key size used.
            Using a portion of the nonce for a random value will decrease the number of messages that a single key can be used for.
            Increasing the key size may require more resources in the constrained device.
            See sections 5 and 10 of <xref target="RFC3610"/> for more information.
          </t>
          
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="ChaCha20 and Poly1305">
        <t>
          ChaCha20 and Poly1305 combined together is a new AEAD mode that is defined in <xref target="RFC7539"/>.
          This is a new algorithm defined to be a cipher which is not AES and thus would not suffer from any future weaknesses found in AES.
          These cryptographic functions are designed to be fast in software only implementations.
        </t>

        <t>
          The ChaCha20/Poly1305 AEAD construction defined in <xref target="RFC7539"/> has no parameterization.
          It takes a 256-bit key and an a 96-bit nonce as well as the plain text and additional data as inputs and produces the cipher text as an option.
          We define one algorithm identifier for this algorithm in <xref target="Table-CHACHA"/>.
        </t>

        <texttable title="Algorithm Value for AES-GCM" anchor="Table-CHACHA">
          <ttcol align='left'>name</ttcol>
          <ttcol align='left'>value</ttcol>
          <ttcol align='left'>description</ttcol>
          <c>ChaCha20/Poly1305</c>        <c>11</c>        <c>ChaCha20/Poly1305 w/ 256-bit key</c>
        </texttable>
        
        <t>
          Keys may be obtained either from a key structure or from a recipient structure.
          If the key obtained from a key structure, the key type MUST be 'Symmetric'.
          Implementations creating and validating MAC values MUST validate that the key type, key length and algorithm are correct and appropriate for the entities involved.
        </t>

        <section title="Security Considerations">
          <t>
            The pair of key, nonce MUST be unique for every invocation of the algorithm.
            Nonce counters are considered to be an acceptable way of ensuring that they are unique.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Key Derivation Functions (KDF)">
      <t>
        Key Derivation Functions (KDFs) are used to take some secret value and generate a different one.
        The original secret values come in three basic flavors:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>Secrets which are uniformly random:  This is the type of secret which is created by a good random number generator.</t>
          <t>Secrets which are not uniformly random: This is type of secret which is created by operations like key agreement.</t>
          <t>Secrets which are not random: This is the type of secret that people generate for things like passwords.</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>
        General KDF functions work well with the first type of secret, can do reasonable well with the second type of secret and generally do poorly with the last type of secret.
        None of the KDF functions in this section are designed to deal with the type of secrets that are used for passwords.
        Functions like PBSE2 <xref target="RFC2898"/> need to be used for that type of secret.
      </t>

      <t>
        Many functions are going to handle the first two type of secrets differently.
        The KDF function defined in <xref target="HKDF"/> can use different underlying constructions if the secret is uniformly random than if the secret is not uniformly random.
        This is reflected in the set of algorithms defined for HKDF.
      </t>

      <t>
        When using KDF functions, one component that is generally included is context information.
        Context information is used to allow for different keying information to be derived from the same secret.
        The use of context based keying material is considered to be a good security practice.
        This document defines a single context structure and a single KDF function.
      </t>
      
      <section title="HMAC-based Extract-and-Expand Key Derivation Function (HKDF)" anchor="HKDF">
        <t> 
          The HKDF key derivation algorithm is defined in <xref target="RFC5869"/>.
        </t>

        <t>
          The HKDF algorithm is defined to take a number of inputs
          These inputs are:

          <list style="none">
            <t>
              secret - a shared value that is secret.
              Secrets may be either previously shared or derived from operations like a DH key agreement.
            </t>

            <t>
              salt - an optional public value that is used to change the generation process.
              If specified, the salt is carried using the 'salt' algorithm parameter.
              While <xref target="RFC5869"/> suggests that the length of the salt be the same as the length of the underlying hash value, any amount of salt will improve the security as different key values will be generated.
              A parameter to carry the salt is defined in <xref target="HKDF_Alg_Params"/>.
              This parameter is protected by being included in the key computation and does not need to be separately authenticated.
            </t>

            <t>
              length - the number of bytes of output that need to be generated.
            </t>

            <t>
              context information - Information that describes the context in which the resulting value will be used.
              Making this information specific to the context that the material is going to be used ensures that the resulting material will always be unique.
              The context structure used is encoded into the algorithm identifier.
            </t>

            <t>
              hash function - The underlying hash function to be used in the HKDF algorithm.
              The hash function is encoded into the HKDF algorithm selection.
            </t>

          </list>
        </t>

        <t>
          HKDF is defined to use HMAC as the underlying PRF.
          However, it is possible to use other functions in the same construct to provide a different KDF function that may be more appropriate in the constrained world.
          Specifically, one can use AES-CBC-MAC as the PRF for the expand step, but not for the extract step.
          When using a good random shared secret of the correct length, the extract step can be skipped.
          The extract cannot be skipped if the secret is not uniformly random, for example if it is the result of a ECDH key agreement step.
        </t>

        <t>
          The algorithms defined in this document are found in <xref target="table-hkdf"/>
        </t>

        <texttable title="HKDF algorithms" anchor="table-hkdf">
          <ttcol>name</ttcol>
          <ttcol>hash</ttcol>
          <ttcol>Skip extract</ttcol>
          <ttcol>context</ttcol>
          <c>HKDF SHA-256</c>       <c>SHA-256</c>      <c>no</c>       <c>XXX</c>
          <c>HKDF SHA-512</c>       <c>SHA-512</c>      <c>no</c>       <c>XXX</c>
          <c>HKDF AES-MAC-128</c>   <c>AES-CBC-128</c>  <c>yes</c>      <c>HKDF using AES-MAC as the PRF w/ 128-bit key</c>
          <c>HKDF AES-MAC-256</c>   <c>AES-CBC-128</c>  <c>yes</c>      <c>HKDF using AES-MAC as the PRF w/ 256-bit key</c>
        </texttable>

        <texttable title="HKDF Algorithm Parameters" anchor="HKDF_Alg_Params">
          <ttcol>name</ttcol>
          <ttcol>label</ttcol>
          <ttcol>type</ttcol>
          <ttcol>description</ttcol>
          <c>salt</c>   <c>-20</c>      <c>bstr</c>     <c>Random salt</c>
        </texttable>

      </section>

      <section title="Context Information Structure" anchor="context">
        <t>
          The context information structure is used to ensure that the derived keying material is "bound" to the context of the transaction.
          The context information structure used here is based on that defined in <xref target="SP800-56A"/>.
          By using CBOR for the encoding of the context information structure, we automatically get the same type of type and length separation of fields that is obtained by the use of ASN.1.
          This means that there is no need to encode the lengths for the base elements as it is done by the JOSE encoding.
          <cref source="Ilari">
            Look to see if we need to be clearer about how the fields defined in the table are transported and thus why they have labels.
          </cref>
        </t>

        <t>
          The context information structure refers to PartyU and PartyV as the two parties which are doing the key derivation.
          Unless the application protocol defines differently, we assign PartyU to the entity that is creating the message and PartyV to the entity that is receiving the message.
          By doing this association, different keys will be derived for each direction as the context information is different in each direction.
        </t>

        <t>
          Application protocols are free to define the roles differently.
          For example, they could assign the PartyU role to the entity that initiates the connection and allow directly sending multiple messages over the connection in both directions without changing the role information.
        </t>

        <t>
          The use of a transaction identifier, either in one of the supplemental fields or as the salt if one is using HKDF, ensures that a unique key is generated for each set of transactions.
          Combining nonce fields with the transaction identifier provides a method so that a different key is used for each message in each direction.
        </t>

        <t>
          The context structure is built from information that is known to both entities.
          Some of the information is known only to the two entities, some is implied based on the application and some is explicitly transported as part of the message.
          The information that can be carried in the message, parameters have been defined and can be found in <xref target="KDF_Context_Alg_Params"/>.
          These parameters are designed to be placed in the unprotected bucket of the recipient structure.
          (They do not need to be in the protected bucket since they already are included in the cryptographic computation by virtue of being included in the context structure.)
        </t>

        <t>
          We encode the context specific information using a CBOR array type.
          The fields in the array are:

          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="AlgorithmID">
              This field indicates the algorithm for which the key material will be used.
              This field is required to be present and is a copy of the algorithm identifier in the message.
              The field exists in the context information so that if the same environment is used for different algorithms, then completely different keys will be generated each of those algorithms.
              (This practice means if algorithm A is broken and  thus can is easier to find, the key derived for algorithm B will not be the same as the key for algorithm B.)
            </t>

            <t hangText="PartyUInfo">
              This field holds information about party U.
              The PartyUInfo is encoded as a CBOR struture.
              The elements of PartyUInfo are encoded in the order presented, however if the element does not exist no element is placed in the array.
              The elements of the PartyUInfo array are:
              
              <list style="hanging">
                <t hangText="identity">
                  This contains the identity information for party U.
                  The identities can be assigned in one of two manners.
                  Firstly, a protocol can assign identities based on roles.
                  For example, the roles of "client" and "server" may be assigned to different entities in the protocol.
                  Each entity would then use the correct label for the data they they send or receive.
                  The second way is for a protocol to assign identities is to use a name based on a naming system (i.e. DNS, X.509 names).
                  <vspace/>
                  We define an algorithm parameter 'PartyU identity' that can be used to carry identity information in the message.
                  However, identity information is often known as part of the protocol and can thus be inferred rather than made explicit.
                  If identity information is carried in the message, applications SHOULD have a way of validating the supplied identity information.
                  The identity information does not need to be specified and can be left as absent.
                  <vspace/>
                  The identity value supplied will be integrity checked as part of the key derivation process.
                  If the identity string is wrong, then the wrong key will be created.
                </t>

                <t hangText="nonce">
                  This contains a one time nonce value.
                  The nonce can either be implicit from the protocol or carried as a value in the unprotected headers.
                  <vspace/>
                  We define an algorithm parameter 'PartyU nonce' that can be used to carry this value in the message
                  However, the nonce value could be determined by the application and the value determined from elsewhere.
                  <vspace/>
                  This item is optional and can be absent.
                </t>

                <t hangText="other">
                  This contains other information that is defined by the protocol.
                  <vspace/>
                  This item is optional and can be absent.
                </t>
              </list>
            </t>

            <t hangText="PartyVInfo">
              M00TODO: Copy down from PartyUInfo when that text is ready.
            </t>

            <t hangText="SuppPubInfo">
              This field contains public information that is mutually known to both parties.
              
              <list style="hanging">
                <t hangText="keyDataLength">
                  This is set to the number of bits of the desired output value.
                  (This practice means if algorithm A can use two different key lengths, the key derived for longer key size will not contain the key for shorter key size as a prefix.)
                </t>

                <t hangText="protected">
                  This field contains the protected parameter field.
                </t>

                <t hangText="other">
                  The field other is for free form data defined by the application.
                  An example is that an application could defined two different strings to be placed here to generate different keys for a data stream vs a control stream.
                  This field is optional and will only be present if the application defines a structure for this information.
                  Applications that define this SHOULD use CBOR to encode the data so that types and lengths are correctly include.
                </t>
              </list>
            </t>

            <t hangText="SuppPrivInfo">
              This field contains private information that is mutually known information.
              An example of this information would be a pre-existing shared secret.
              The field is optional and will only be present if the application defines a structure for this information.
              Applications that define this SHOULD use CBOR to encode the data so that types and lengths are correctly include.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <texttable title="Context Algorithm Parameters" anchor="KDF_Context_Alg_Params">
          <ttcol>name</ttcol>
          <ttcol>label</ttcol>
          <ttcol>type</ttcol>
          <ttcol>description</ttcol>
          <c>PartyU identity</c>   <c>-21</c>      <c>bstr</c>          <c>Party U identity Information</c>
          <c>PartyU nonce</c>      <c>-22</c>      <c>bstr / int</c>    <c>Party U provided nonce</c>
          <c>PartyU other</c>      <c>-23</c>      <c>bstr</c>          <c>Party U other provided information</c>
          <c>PartyV identity</c>   <c>-24</c>      <c>bstr</c>          <c>Party V identity Information</c>
          <c>PartyV nonce</c>      <c>-25</c>      <c>bstr / int</c>    <c>Party V provided nonce</c>
          <c>PartyV other</c>      <c>-26</c>      <c>bstr</c>          <c>Party V other provided information</c>
        </texttable>

        <!-- RFC EDITOR - Please make sure the following paragraphs have been removed. -->

      <t>
        Text from here to start of next section to be removed
      </t>

        <figure><artwork type='CDDL'>
<![CDATA[
COSE_KDF_Context = [
    AlgorithmID : int / tstr,
    PartyUInfo : [
        ? nonce : bstr / int,
        ? identity : bstr,
        ? other : bstr
    ],
    PartyVInfo : [
        ? nonce : bstr,
        ? identity : bstr / tstr,
        ? other : bstr
    ],
    SuppPubInfo : [
        keyDataLength : uint,
        protected : bstr,
        ? other : bstr
    ],
    ? SuppPrivInfo : bstr
]
]]></artwork></figure>


      </section>


    </section>

    <section title="Recipient Algorithm Classes" anchor="key-management-algs">
      <t>
        Recipient algorithms can be defined into a number of different classes.
        COSE has the ability to support many classes of recipient algorithms.
        In this section, a number of classes are listed and then a set of algorithms are specified for each of the classes.
        The names of the recipient algorithm classes used here are the same as are defined in <xref target="RFC7517"/>.
        Other specifications use different terms for the recipient algorithm classes or do not support some of our recipient algorithm classes.
      </t>

      

      <section title="Direct Encryption">
          <t>
            The direct encryption class algorithms share a secret between the sender and the recipient that is used either directly or after manipulation as the content key.
            When direct encryption mode is used, it MUST be the only mode used on the message.
          </t>

          <t>
            The COSE_encrypt structure for the recipient is organized as follows:
          </t>

          <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                The 'protected' field MUST be a zero length item if it is not used in the computation of the content key.
              </t>
              
              <t>
                The 'alg' parameter MUST be present.
              </t>

              <t>
                A parameter identifying the shared secret SHOULD be present.
              </t>

              <t>
                The 'ciphertext' field MUST be a zero length item.
              </t>
              
              <t>
                The 'recipients' field MUST be absent.
              </t>
              
            </list>
          </t>

          <section title="Direct Key">
            <t>
              This recipient algorithm is the simplest, the supplied key is directly used as the key for the next layer down in the message.
              There are no algorithm parameters defined for this algorithm.
              The algorithm identifier value is assigned  in <xref target="table-direct"/>.
            </t>

            <t>
              When this algorithm is used, the protected field MUST be zero length.
              The key type MUST be 'Symmetric'.
            </t>

            <texttable title="Direct Key" anchor="table-direct">
              <ttcol align='left'>name</ttcol>
              <ttcol align='left'>value</ttcol>
              <ttcol align='left'>description</ttcol>
              <c>direct</c>          <c>-6</c>       <c>Direct use of CEK</c>
            </texttable>


            <section title="Security Considerations">
              <t>
                This recipient algorithm has several potential problems that need to be considered:
                <list style="symbols">
                  <t>
                    These keys need to have some method to be regularly updated over time.
                    All of the content encryption algorithms specified in this document have limits on how many times a key can be used without significant loss of security.
                  </t>
                  <t>
                    These keys need to be dedicated to a single algorithm.
                    There have been a number of attacks developed over time when a single key is used for multiple different algorithms.
                    One example of this is the use of a single key both for CBC encryption mode and CBC-MAC authentication mode.
                  </t>
                  <t>
                    Breaking one message means all messages are broken.
                    If an adversary succeeds in determining the key for a single message, then the key for all messages is also determined.
                  </t>
                </list>
              </t>
            </section>
          </section>

          <section title="Direct Key with KDF">
            <t>
              These recipient algorithms take a common shared secret between the two parties and applies the HKDF function (<xref target="HKDF"/>) using the context structure defined in <xref target="context"/> to transform the shared secret into the necessary key.
              Either the 'salt' parameter of HKDF or the partyU 'nonce' parameter of the context structure MUST be present.
              This parameter can be generated either randomly or deterministically, the requirement is that it be a unique value for the key pair in question.
            </t>

            <t>
              If the salt/nonce value is generated randomly, then it is suggested that the length of the random value be the same length as the hash function underlying HKDF.
              While there is no way to guarantee that it will be unique, there is a high probability that it will be unique.
              If the salt/nonce value is generated deterministically, it can be guaranteed to be unique and thus there is no length requirement.
            </t>

            <t>
              A new IV must be used if the same key is used in more than one message.
              The IV can be modified in a predictable manner, a random manner or an unpredictable manner.
              One unpredictable manner that can be used is to use the HKDF function to generate the IV.
              If HKDF is used for generating the IV, the algorithm identifier is set to "IV-GENERATION".
            </t>

            <t>
              When these algorithms are used, the key type MUST be 'symmetric'.
            </t>
            
            <t>
              The set of algorithms defined in this document can be found in <xref target="table-direct-kdf"/>.
            </t>

            <texttable title="Direct Key" anchor="table-direct-kdf">
              <ttcol align='left'>name</ttcol>
              <ttcol align='left'>value</ttcol>
              <ttcol align='left'>KDF</ttcol>
              <ttcol align='left'>description</ttcol>
              <c>direct+HKDF-SHA-256</c>      <c>*</c>        <c>HKDF SHA-256</c>     <c>Shared secret w/ HKDF and SHA-256</c>
              <c>direct+HKDF-SHA-512</c>      <c>*</c>        <c>HKDF SHA-512</c>     <c>Shared secret w/ HKDF and SHA-512</c>
              <c>direct+HKDF-AES-128</c>      <c>*</c>        <c>HKDF AES-MAC-128</c> <c>Shared secret w/ AES-MAC 128-bit key</c>
              <c>direct+HKDF-AES-256</c>      <c>*</c>        <c>HKDF AES-MAC-256</c> <c>Shared secret w/ AES-MAC 256-bit key</c>
            </texttable>

            <section title="Security Considerations">
              <t>
                The shared secret need to have some method to be regularly updated over time.
                The shared secret is forming the basis of trust, although not used directly it should still be subject to scheduled rotation.
              </t>
            </section>
          </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Key Wrapping">
        <t>
          In key wrapping mode, the CEK is randomly generated and that key is then encrypted by a shared secret between the sender and the recipient.
          All of the currently defined key wrapping algorithms for JOSE (and thus for COSE) are AE algorithms.
          Key wrapping mode is considered to be superior to direct encryption if the system has any capability for doing random key generation.
          This is because the shared key is used to wrap random data rather than data  has some degree of organization and may in fact be repeating the same content.
        </t>

        <t>
          The COSE_encrypt structure for the recipient is organized as follows:
        </t>

        <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              The 'protected' field MUST be absent if the key wrap algorithm is an AE algorithm.
            </t>
            <t>
              The 'recipients' field is normally absent, but can be used.
              Applications MUST deal with a recipients field present, not being able to decrypt that recipient is an acceptable way of dealing with it.
              Failing to process the message is not an acceptable way of dealing with it.
            </t>
            <t>
              The plain text to be encrypted is the key from next layer down
              (usually the content layer).
            </t>
            <t>
              At a minimum, the 'unprotected' field MUST contain the 'alg'
              parameter and SHOULD contain a parameter identifying the shared secret.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <section title="AES Key Wrapping" anchor="key_wrap_algs">
          <t>
            The AES Key Wrapping algorithm is defined in <xref target="RFC3394"/>.
            This algorithm uses an AES key to wrap a value that is a multiple of 64-bits, as such it can be used to wrap a key for any of the content encryption algorithms defined in this document.
            <!--  Don't care about this anymore
            <cref source="JLS">
              Do we also want to document the use of RFC 5649 as well?  
              It allows for other sizes of keys that might be used for HMAC - i.e. a 200 bit key.
              The algorithm exists, but I do not personally know of any standard uses of it.
              </cref>
              -->
            The algorithm requires a single fixed parameter, the initial value.
            This is fixed to the value specified in Section 2.2.3.1 of  <xref target="RFC3394"/>.
            There are no public parameters that vary on a per invocation basis.
          </t>

          <t>
            Keys may be obtained either from a key structure or from a recipient structure.
            If the key obtained from a key structure, the key type MUST be 'Symmetric'.
            Implementations creating and validating MAC values MUST validate that the key type, key length and algorithm are correct and appropriate for the entities involved.
          </t>
          
          
          <texttable title="AES Key Wrap Algorithm Values" anchor="table_aes_keywrap">
            <ttcol align='left'>name</ttcol>
            <ttcol align='left'>value</ttcol>
            <ttcol align='left'>key size</ttcol>
            <ttcol align='left'>description</ttcol>
            <c>A128KW</c>       <c>-3</c>       <c>128</c>      <c>AES Key Wrap w/ 128-bit key</c>
            <c>A192KW</c>       <c>-4</c>       <c>192</c>      <c>AES Key Wrap w/ 192-bit key</c>
            <c>A256KW</c>       <c>-5</c>       <c>256</c>      <c>AES Key Wrap w/ 256-bit key</c>
          </texttable>

          <section title="Security Considerations for AES-KW">
              <t>
                The shared secret need to have some method to be regularly updated over time.
                The shared secret is forming the basis of trust, although not used directly it should still be subject to scheduled rotation.
              </t>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Key Encryption">
        <t>
          Key Encryption mode is also called key transport mode in some standards.
          Key Encryption mode differs from Key Wrap mode in that it uses an asymmetric encryption algorithm rather than a symmetric encryption algorithm to protect the key.
          This document defines one Key Encryption mode algorithm.
        </t>

        <t>
          When using a key encryption algorithm, the COSE_encrypt structure for the recipient is organized as follows:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              The 'protected' field MUST be absent.
            </t>
            
            <t>
              The plain text to be encrypted is the key from next layer down
              (usually the content layer).
            </t>
            
            <t>
              At a minimum, the 'unprotected' field MUST contain the 'alg'
              parameter and SHOULD contain a parameter identifying the asymmetric key.
            </t>
            
          </list>
        </t>

        <section title="RSAES-OAEP">
          <t>
            RSAES-OAEP is an asymmetric key encryption algorithm.
            The defintion of RSAEA-OAEP can be find in Section 7.1 of <xref target="RFC3447"/>.
            The algorithm is parameterized using a masking generation function (mgf), a hash function (h) and encoding parameters (P).
            For the algorithm identifiers defined in this section:
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>mgf is always set to MFG1 from <xref target="RFC3447"/> and uses the same hash function as h.</t>
              <t>P is always set to the empty octet string.</t>
            </list>
            <xref target="table-RSA-OAEP"/> summarizes the rest of the values.
          </t>
          
          <texttable anchor="table-RSA-OAEP" title="RSAES-OAEP Algorithm Values">
            <ttcol align='left'>name</ttcol>
            <ttcol align='left'>value</ttcol>
            <ttcol align='left'>hash</ttcol>
            <ttcol align='left'>description</ttcol>
            <c>RSAES-OAEP w/SHA-256</c>     <c>-25</c>       <c>SHA-256</c>       <c>RSAES OAEP w/ SHA-256</c>
            <c>RSAES-OAEP w/SHA-512</c>     <c>-26</c>       <c>SHA-512</c>       <c>RSAES OAEP w/ SHA-512</c>
          </texttable>

          <t>
            The key type MUST be 'RSA'.
          </t>

          <section title="Security Considerations for RSAES-OAEP">
            
            <t>
              A key size of 2048 bits or larger MUST be used with these algorithms.
              This key size corresponds roughly to the same strength as provided by a 128-bit symmetric encryption algorithm.
            </t>

            <t>
              It is highly recommended that checks on the key length  be done before starting a decryption operation.
              One potential denial of service operation is to provide encrypted objects using either abnormally long or oddly sized RSA modulus values.
              Implementations SHOULD be able to encrypt and decrypt with modulus between 2048 and 16K bits in length.
              Applications can impose additional restrictions on the length of the modulus.
            </t>
          </section>
        </section>

      </section>

      <section title="Direct Key Agreement">
        <t>
          The 'direct key agreement' class of recipient algorithms uses a key agreement method to create a shared secret.
          A KDF is then applied to the shared secret to derive a key to be used in protecting the data.
          This key is normally used as a CEK or MAC key, but could be used for other purposes if more than two layers are in use (see <xref target="three-layer"/>).
        </t>

        <t>
          The most commonly used key agreement algorithm used is Diffie-Hellman, but other variants exist.
          Since COSE is designed for a store and forward environment rather than an on-line environment, many of the DH variants cannot be used as the receiver of the message cannot provide any key material.
          One side-effect of this is that perfect forward security is not achievable, a static key will always be used for the receiver of the COSE message.
        </t>

        <t>
          Two variants of DH that are easily supported are:
          <list>
            <t>
-              Ephemeral-Static DH: where the sender of the message creates a one time DH key and uses a static key for the recipient.
              The use of the ephemeral sender key means that no additional random input is needed as this is randomly generated for each message.
            </t>

            <t>
              Static-Static DH: where a static key is used for both the sender and the recipient.
              The use of static keys allows for recipient to get a weak version of data origination for the message.
              When static-static key agreement is used, then some piece of unique data is require to ensure that a different key is created for each message
            </t>
          </list>
          
          In this specification, both variants are specified.
          This has been done to provide the weak data origination option for use with MAC operations.
        </t>

        <t>
          When direct key agreement mode is used, there MUST be only one recipient in the message.
          This method creates the key directly and that makes it difficult to mix with additional recipients.
          If multiple recipients are needed, then the version with key wrap needs to be used.
        </t>

        <t>
          The COSE_encrypt structure for the recipient is organized as follows:
        </t>

        <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              The 'protected' field MUST be absent.
            </t>
            <t>
              At a minimum, the 'unprotected' field MUST contain the 'alg' parameter and SHOULD contain a parameter identifying the recipient's asymmetric key.
            </t>
            <t>
              The 'unprotected' field MUST contain the 'epk' parameter.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <section title="ECDH">
          <t>
            The basic mathematics for Elliptic Curve Diffie-Hellman can be found in <xref target="RFC6090"/>.
          </t>

          <t>
            ECDH is parameterized by the following:
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                Curve Type/Curve: 
                The curve selected controls not only the size of the shared secret, but the mathematics for computing the shared secret.
                The curve selected also controls how a point in the curve is represented and what happens for the identity points on the curve.
                In this specification we allow for a number of different curves to be used.
                The curves are defined in <xref target="table-ec-curves"/>.
                <vspace/>
                Since the only the math is changed by changing the curve, the curve is not fixed for any of the algorithm identifiers we define, instead it is defined by the points used.
              </t>
              
              <t>
                Ephemeral-static or static-static:
                The key agreement process may be done using either a static or an ephemeral key at the senders side.
                When using ephemeral keys, the sender MUST generate a new ephemeral key for every key agreement operation.
                The ephemeral key is placed in in the 'ephemeral key' parameter and MUST be present for all algorithm identifiers which use ephemeral keys.
                When using static keys, the sender MUST either generate a new random value placed in either in the KDF parameters or the context structure.
                For the KDF functions used, this means either in the 'salt' parameter for HKDF (<xref target="HKDF_Alg_Params"/>) or in in the 'PartyU nonce' parameter for the context struture (<xref target="KDF_Context_Alg_Params"/>) MUST be present.
                (Both may be present if desired.)
                The value in the parameter MUST be unique for the key pair being used.
                It is acceptable to use a global counter which is incremented for every static-static operation and use the resulting value.
                When using static keys, the static key needs to be identified to the recipient.
                The static key can be identified either by providing the key ('static key') or by providing a key identifier for the static key ('static key id').
                Both of these parameters are defined in <xref target="table-ecdh-es-parameter-table"/>
              </t>
              
              <t>
                Key derivation algorithm:
                The result of an ECDH key agreement process does not provide a uniformly random secret, as such it needs to be run through a KDF in order to produce a usable key.
                Processing the secret through a KDF also allows for the introduction of both context material, how the key is going to be used, and one time material in the even to of a static-static key agreement.
              </t>

              <t>
                Key Wrap algorithm:
                The key wrap algorithm can be 'none' if the result of the KDF is going to be used as the key directly.
                This option, along with static-static, should be used if knowledge about the sender is desired.
                If 'none' is used then the content layer encryption algorithm size is value fed to the context structure.
                Support is also provided for any of the key wrap algorithms defined in section <xref target="key_wrap_algs"/>.
                If one of these options is used, the input key size to the key wrap algorithm is the value fed into the context structure as the key size.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>

          <t>
            The set of algorithms direct ECDH defined in this document are found in <xref target="table-ecdh-es-table"/>.
          </t>

          <texttable title="ECDH Algorithm Values" anchor="table-ecdh-es-table">
            <ttcol align='left'>name</ttcol>
            <ttcol align='left'>value</ttcol>
            <ttcol align='left'>KDF</ttcol>
            <ttcol align='left'>Ephemeral-Static</ttcol>
            <ttcol align='left'>Key Wrap</ttcol>
            <ttcol align='left'>description</ttcol>
            
            <c>ECDH-ES + HKDF-256</c>      <c>50</c>        <c>HKDF - SHA-256</c>     <c>yes</c>      <c>none</c>       <c>ECDH ES w/ HKDF - generate key directly</c>
            <c>ECDH-ES + HKDF-512</c>      <c>51</c>        <c>HKDF - SHA-256</c>     <c>yes</c>      <c>none</c>       <c>ECDH ES w/ HKDF - generate key directly</c>
            <c>ECDH-SS + HKDF-256</c>      <c>52</c>        <c>HKDF - SHA-256</c>     <c>no</c>       <c>none</c>       <c>ECDH ES w/ HKDF - generate key directly</c>
            <c>ECDH-SS + HKDF-512</c>      <c>53</c>        <c>HKDF - SHA-256</c>     <c>no</c>       <c>none</c>       <c>ECDH ES w/ HKDF - generate key directly</c>
            <c>ECDH-ES+A128KW</c>          <c>54</c>        <c>HKDF - SHA-256</c>     <c>yes</c>      <c>A128KW</c>     <c>ECDH ES w/ Concat KDF and AES Key wrap w/ 128 bit key</c>
            <c>ECDH-ES+A192KW</c>          <c>55</c>        <c>HKDF - SHA-256</c>     <c>yes</c>      <c>A192KW</c>     <c>ECDH ES w/ Concat KDF and AES Key wrap w/ 192 bit key</c>
            <c>ECDH-ES+A256KW</c>          <c>56</c>        <c>HKDF - SHA-256</c>     <c>yes</c>      <c>A256KW</c>     <c>ECDH ES w/ Concat KDF and AES Key wrap w/ 256 bit key</c>
            <c>ECDH-SS+A128KW</c>          <c>57</c>        <c>HKDF - SHA-256</c>     <c>no</c>       <c>A128KW</c>     <c>ECDH SS w/ Concat KDF and AES Key wrap w/ 128 bit key</c>
            <c>ECDH-SS+A192KW</c>          <c>58</c>        <c>HKDF - SHA-256</c>     <c>no</c>       <c>A192KW</c>     <c>ECDH SS w/ Concat KDF and AES Key wrap w/ 192 bit key</c>
            <c>ECDH-SS+A256KW</c>          <c>59</c>        <c>HKDF - SHA-256</c>     <c>no</c>       <c>A256KW</c>     <c>ECDH SS w/ Concat KDF and AES Key wrap w/ 256 bit key</c>

          </texttable>


          <texttable title="ECDH Algorithm Parameters" anchor="table-ecdh-es-parameter-table">
            <ttcol>name</ttcol>
            <ttcol>label</ttcol>
            <ttcol>type</ttcol>
            <ttcol>algorithm</ttcol>
            <ttcol>description</ttcol>
            <c>ephemeral key</c>        <c>-1</c>       <c>COSE_Key</c>         <c>ECDH-ES</c>  <c>Ephemeral Public key for the sender</c>
            <c>static key</c>           <c>-2</c>       <c>COSE_Key</c>         <c>ECDH-ES</c>  <c>Static Public key for the sender</c>
            <c>static key id </c>       <c>-3</c>       <c>bstr</c>             <c>ECDH-SS</c>  <c>Static Public key identifier for the sender</c>
          </texttable>

          <t>
            This document defines these algorithms to be used with the curves P-256, P-384, P-521.
            Implementations MUST verify that the key type and curve are correct, different curves are restricted to different key types.
            Implementations MUST verify that the curve and algorithm are appropriate for the entities involved.
          </t>

        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Key Agreement with KDF" anchor="ECDH-Direct">
        <t>
          Key Agreement with Key Wrapping uses a randomly generated CEK.
          The CEK is then encrypted using a Key Wrapping algorithm and a key derived from the shared secret computed by the key agreement algorithm.
        </t>

        <t>
          The COSE_encrypt structure for the recipient is organized as follows:
        </t>

        <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              The 'protected' field is fed into the KDF context structure.
            </t>
            <t>
              The plain text to be encrypted is the key from next layer down (usually the content layer).
            </t>
            <t>
              The 'alg' parameter MUST be present in the layer.
            </t>
            <t>
              A parameter identifying the recipient's key SHOULD be present.
              A parameter identifying the senders key SHOULD be present.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <section title="ECDH">

          <t>
            These algorithms are defined in <xref target="table-ecdh-es-table"/>.
          </t>
        </section>
        
      </section>

      <!--  Comment out password based algorithms.   Issue #6 - https://github.com/cose-wg/cose-issues/issues/6
           
      <section title="Password">
        <t>
          <cref source="JLS">
            Do we want/need to support this?
            JOSE did it mainly to support the encryption of private keys.
          </cref>
        </t>
        
        <section title="PBES2">
          <texttable>
            <ttcol align='left'>name</ttcol>
            <ttcol align='left'>value</ttcol>
            <ttcol align='left'>description</ttcol>
            <c>PBES2-HS256+A128KW</c>        <c>*</c>        <c>PBES2 w/ HMAC SHA-256 and AES Key wrap w/ 128 bit key</c>
            <c>PBES2-HS384+A192KW</c>        <c>*</c>        <c>PBES2 w/ HMAC SHA-384 and AES Key wrap w/ 192 bit key</c>
            <c>PBES2-HS512+A256KW</c>        <c>*</c>        <c>PBES2 w/ HMAC SHA-512 and AES Key wrap w/ 256 bit key</c>
          </texttable>
        </section>
        </section>
        -->
    </section>

    <section title="Keys" anchor="Key-specific-labels">
      <t>
        The COSE_Key object defines a way to hold a single key object, it is still required that the members of individual key types be defined.
        This section of the document is where we define an initial set of members for specific key types.
      </t>

      <t>
        For each of the key types, we define both public and private members.
        The public members are what is transmitted to others for their usage.
        We define private members mainly for the purpose of archival of keys by individuals.
        However, there are some circumstances where private keys may be distributed by various entities in a protocol.
        Examples include:  Entities which have poor random number generation.
        Centralized key creation for multi-cast type operations.
        Protocols where a shared secret is used as a bearer token for authorization purposes.
      </t>

      <t>
        Key types are identified by the 'kty' member of the COSE_Key object.
        In this document we define four values for the member.
      </t>

      <texttable title="Key Type Values" anchor="table_key_types">
        <ttcol>name</ttcol>
        <ttcol>value</ttcol>
        <ttcol>description</ttcol>
<!--        <c>EC1</c>      <c>1</c>        <c>Elliptic Curve Keys w/ X Coordinate only</c> -->
        <c>EC2</c>      <c>2</c>        <c>Elliptic Curve Keys w/ X,Y Coordinate pair</c>
        <c>RSA</c>      <c>3</c>        <c>RSA Keys</c>
        <c>Symmetric</c><c>4</c>        <c>Symmetric Keys</c>
        <c>Reserved</c> <c>0</c>        <c>This value is reserved</c>
      </texttable>
      
      <section title="Elliptic Curve Keys">
        <t>
          Two different key structures could be defined for Elliptic Curve keys.
          One version uses both an x and a y coordinate, potentially with point compression.
          This is the traditional EC point representation that is used in <xref target="RFC5480"/>.
          
          The other version uses only the x coordinate as the y coordinate is either to be recomputed or not needed for the key agreement operation
          Currently no algorithms are defined using this key structure.
        </t>
        
        <texttable title="EC Curves" anchor="table-ec-curves">
          <ttcol>name</ttcol>
          <ttcol>key type</ttcol>
          <ttcol>value</ttcol>
          <ttcol>description</ttcol>
          <c>P-256</c>        <c>EC2</c>      <c>1</c>       <c>NIST P-256 also known as secp256r1</c>
          <c>P-384</c>        <c>EC2</c>      <c>2</c>       <c>NIST P-384 also known as secp384r1</c>
          <c>P-521</c>        <c>EC2</c>      <c>3</c>       <c>NIST P-521 also known as secp521r1</c>
        </texttable>

        <section title="Double Coordinate Curves" anchor="EC2-Keys">
          <t>
            The traditional way of sending EC curves has been to send either both the x and y coordinates, or the x coordinate and a sign bit for the y coordinate.
            The latter encoding has not been recommend in the IETF due to potential IPR issues with Certicom.
            However, for operations in constrained environments, the ability to shrink a message by not sending the y coordinate is potentially useful.
          </t>
          
          <t>
            For EC keys with both coordinates, the 'kty' member is set to 2 (EC2).
            The key parameters defined in this section are summarized in <xref target="table-ec2-keys"/>.
            The members that are defined for this key type are:
            
            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="crv">
                contains an identifier of the curve to be used with the key.
                The curves defined in this document for this key type can be found in <xref target="table-ec-curves"/>.
                Other curves may be registered in the future and private curves can be used as well.
              </t>
              
              <t hangText="x">
                contains the x coordinate for the EC point.
                The integer is converted to an octet string as defined in <xref target="SEC1"/>.
                Zero octets MUST NOT be removed from the front of the octet string.

                <cref source="JLS">
                  Should we use the bignum encoding for x, y and d instead of bstr?
                </cref>
              </t>
              
              <t hangText="y">
                contains either the sign bit or the value of y coordinate for the EC point.
                For the value, the integer is converted to an octet string as defined in <xref target="SEC1"/>.
                Zero octets MUST NOT be removed from the front of the octet string.
                For the sign bit, the value is true if the value of y is positive.
              </t>
              
              <t hangText="d">
                contains the private key.
              </t>
              
            </list>
          </t>

          <t>
            For public keys, it is REQUIRED that 'crv', 'x' and 'y' be present in the structure.
            For private keys, it is REQUIRED that 'crv' and 'd' be present in the structure.
            For private keys, it is RECOMMENDED that 'x' and 'y' also be present, but they can be recomputed from the required elements and omitting them saves on space.
          </t>

          <texttable title="EC Key Parameters" anchor="table-ec2-keys">
            <ttcol>name</ttcol>
            <ttcol>key type</ttcol>
            <ttcol>value</ttcol>
            <ttcol>type</ttcol>
            <ttcol>description</ttcol>
            <c>crv</c>    <c>2</c>      <c>-1</c>       <c>int / tstr</c>       <c>EC Curve identifier - Taken from the COSE General Registry</c>
            <c>x</c>      <c>2</c>      <c>-2</c>       <c>bstr</c>             <c>X Coordinate</c>
            <c>y</c>      <c>2</c>      <c>-3</c>       <c>bstr / bool</c>      <c>Y Coordinate</c>
            <c>d</c>      <c>2</c>      <c>-4</c>       <c>bstr</c>             <c>Private key</c>
          </texttable>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="RSA Keys">
        <t>
          This document defines a key structure for both the public and private halves of RSA keys.
          Together, an RSA public key and an RSA private key form an RSA key pair.
          <cref source="JLS">
            Looking at the CBOR specification, the bstr that we are looking in our table below should most likely be specified as big numbers rather than as binary strings.
            This means that we would use the tag 6.2 instead.
            From my reading of the specification, there is no difference in the encoded size of the resulting output.
            The specification of bignum does explicitly allow for integers encoded with leading zeros.
          </cref>
        </t>

        <t>
          The document also provides support for the so-called "multi-prime" RSA where the modulus may have more than two prime factors.
          The benefit of multi-prime RSA is lower computational cost for the decryption and signature primitives.
          For a discussion on how multi-prime affects the security of RSA crypto-systems, the reader is referred to <xref target="MultiPrimeRSA"/>.
        </t>

        <t>
          This document follows the naming convention of <xref target="RFC3447"/> for the naming of the fields of an RSA public or private key.
          The table <xref target="table-rsa-keys"/> provides a summary of the label values and the types associated with each of those labels.
          The requirements for fields for RSA keys are as follows:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              For all keys, 'kty' MUST be present and MUST have a value of 3.
            </t>
            <t>
              For public keys, the fields 'n' and 'e' MUST be present. 
              All other fields defined in <xref target="table-rsa-keys"/> MUST be absent.
            </t>
            <t>
              For private keys with two primes, the fields 'other', 'r_i', 'd_i' and 't_i' MUST be absent, all other fields MUST be present.
            </t>
            <t>
              For private keys with more than two primes, all fields MUST  be present. 
              For the third to nth primes, each of the primes is represented as a map containing the fields 'r_i', 'd_i' and 't_i'. 
              The field 'other' is an array of those maps.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
          
        <texttable title="RSA Key Parameters" anchor="table-rsa-keys">
          <ttcol>name</ttcol>
          <ttcol>key type</ttcol>
          <ttcol>value</ttcol>
          <ttcol>type</ttcol>
          <ttcol>description</ttcol>
          <c>n</c>      <c>3</c>        <c>-1</c>       <c>bstr</c>             <c>Modulus Parameter</c>
          <c>e</c>      <c>3</c>        <c>-2</c>       <c>int</c>              <c>Exponent Parameter</c>
          <c>d</c>      <c>3</c>        <c>-3</c>       <c>bstr</c>             <c>Private Exponent Parameter</c>
          <c>p</c>      <c>3</c>        <c>-4</c>       <c>bstr</c>             <c>First Prime Factor</c>
          <c>q</c>      <c>3</c>        <c>-5</c>       <c>bstr</c>             <c>Second Prime Factor</c>
          <c>dP</c>     <c>3</c>        <c>-6</c>       <c>bstr</c>             <c>First Factor CRT Exponent</c>
          <c>dQ</c>     <c>3</c>        <c>-7</c>       <c>bstr</c>             <c>Second Factor CRT Exponent</c>
          <c>qInv</c>   <c>3</c>        <c>-8</c>       <c>bstr</c>             <c>First CRT Coefficient</c>
          <c>other</c>  <c>3</c>        <c>-9</c>       <c>array</c>            <c>Other Primes Info</c>
          <c>r_i</c>    <c>3</c>        <c>-10</c>      <c>bstr</c>             <c>i-th factor, Prime Factor</c>
          <c>d_i</c>    <c>3</c>        <c>-11</c>      <c>bstr</c>             <c>i-th factor, Factor CRT Exponent</c>
          <c>t_i</c>    <c>3</c>        <c>-12</c>      <c>bstr</c>             <c>i-th factor, Factor CRT Coefficient</c>
        </texttable>
      </section>

      <section title="Symmetric Keys">
        <t>
          Occasionally it is required that a symmetric key be transported between entities.
          This key structure allows for that to happen.
        </t>

        <t>
          For symmetric keys, the 'kty' member is set to 3 (Symmetric).
          The member that is defined for this key type is:
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="k">
              contains the value of the key.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>
          This key structure contains only private key information, care must be taken that it is never transmitted accidentally.
          For public keys, there are no required fields.
          For private keys, it is REQUIRED that 'k' be present in the structure.
        </t>
        
        <texttable title="Symmetric Key Parameters" anchor="table-symmetric-keys">
          <ttcol>name</ttcol>
          <ttcol>key type</ttcol>
          <ttcol>value</ttcol>
          <ttcol>type</ttcol>
          <ttcol>description</ttcol>
          <c>k</c>      <c>4</c>        <c>-1</c>       <c>bstr</c>             <c>Key Value</c>
        </texttable>
      </section>
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="CBOR-Canonical" title="CBOR Encoder Restrictions">

      <t>
        There as been an attempt to limit the number of places where the document 
        needs to impose restrictions on how the CBOR Encoder needs to work.  We have
        managed to narrow it down to the following restrictions:
      </t>

      <t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            The restriction applies to the encoding the Sig_structure, the Enc_structure, and the MAC_structure.
          </t>
          <t>
            The rules for Canonical CBOR (Section 3.9 of RFC 7049) MUST be used in these
            locations.  The main rule that needs to be enforced is that all lengths
            in these structures MUST be encoded such that they are encoded using definite lengths 
            and the minimum length encoding is used.
          </t>
          <t>
            All parsers used SHOULD fail on both parsing and generation if the same label is used twice as a key for the same map.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="iana-considerations" title="IANA Considerations">

      <section anchor="cbor-tag-assignment" title="CBOR Tag assignment">

        <t>
          It is requested that IANA assign the following tags from the “Concise Binary Object Representation (CBOR) Tags” registry.
          It is requested that the tags be assigned in the 24 to 128 value range.
        </t>

        <t>
          The tags to be assigned are:
        </t>

          <texttable>
            <ttcol>Tag Value</ttcol>    <ttcol>Data Item</ttcol>  <ttcol>Semantics</ttcol>
            <c>TBD1</c>                 <c>COSE_Sign</c>                <c>COSE Signed Data Object</c>
            <c>TBD2</c>                 <c>COSE_enveloped</c>           <c>COSE Enveloped Data Object</c>
            <c>TBD3</c>                 <c>COSE_encryptData</c>         <c>COSE Encrypted Data Object</c>
            <c>TBD4</c>                 <c>COSE_Mac</c>                 <c>COSE Mac-ed Data Object</c>
          </texttable>

      </section>

      <!--
      <section anchor="IANA-Top-Level-Keys" title="COSE Object Labels Registry">

        <t>
          It is requested that IANA create a new registry entitled “COSE Object Labels Registry”.
          <cref source="JLS">Finish the registration process.</cref>
        </t>

        <t>
          This table is initially populated by the table in <xref target="Top-Level-Keys"/>.
        </t>

        </section>
      -->
      
      <section anchor="cose-header-key-table" title="COSE Header Parameter Registry">

        <t>
          It is requested that IANA create a new registry entitled “COSE Header Parameters”.
        </t>

        <t>
          The columns of the registry are:

          <list style="hanging">
            
            <t hangText='name'>
              The name is present to make it easier to refer to and discuss the registration entry. 
              The value is not used in the protocol. 
              Names are to be unique in the table.
            </t>
            
            <t hangText='label'>
              This is the value used for the label.
              The label can be either an integer or a string.
              Registration in the table is based on the value of the label requested.
              <!-- these are 1 and 2 byte items -->
              Integer values between 1 and 255 and strings of length 1 are designated as Standards Track Document required.

              <!-- These are 3 byte items -->
              Integer values from 256 to 65535 and strings of length 2 are designated as Specification Required.

              <!-- These are >= 5 byte items -->
              Integer values of greater than 65535 and strings of length greater than 2 are designated as first come first server.

              <!-- These are 1, 2 and 3 byte items -->
              Integer values in the range -1 to -65536 are delegated to the “COSE Header Algorithm Label” registry.

              <!-- These are >= 5 byte items -->
              Integer values beyond -65536 are marked as private use.
            </t>

            <t hangText='value'>
              This contains the CBOR type for the value portion of the label.
            </t>

            <t hangText='value registry'>
              This contains a pointer to the registry used to contain values where the set is limited.
            </t>

            <t hangText='description'>
              This contains a brief description of the header field.
            </t>

            <t hangText='specification'>
              This contains a pointer to the specification defining the header field (where public).
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>
          The initial contents of the registry can be found in <xref target="Header-Table"/>.
          The specification column for all rows in that table should be this document.
        </t>

        <t>
          Additionally, the label of 0 is to be marked as 'Reserved'.
        </t>

      </section>

      
      <section anchor="IANA-Alg-Registry" title="COSE Header Algorithm Label Table">

        <t>
          It is requested that IANA create a new registry entitled “COSE Header Algorithm Labels”.
        </t>

        <t>
          The columns of the registry are:
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText='name'>
              The name is present to make it easier to refer to and discuss the registration entry.  The value is not used in the protocol.
            </t>
            
            <t hangText='algorithm'>
              The algorithm(s) that this registry entry is used for.
              This value is taken from the “COSE Algorithm Value” registry.
              Multiple algorithms can be specified in this entry.
              For the table, the algorithm, label pair MUST be unique.
            </t>
            
            <t hangText='label'>
              This is the value used for the label.
              The label is an integer in the range of -1 to -65536.
            </t>
            
            <t hangText='value'>
              This contains the CBOR type for the value portion of the label.
            </t>
            
            <t hangText='value registry'>
              This contains a pointer to the registry used to contain values where the set is limited.
            </t>
            
            <t hangText='description'>
              This contains a brief description of the header field.
            </t>
            
            <t hangText='specification'>
              This contains a pointer to the specification defining the header field (where public).
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>
          The initial contents of the registry can be found in: <xref target="HKDF_Alg_Params"/>,  <xref target="KDF_Context_Alg_Params"/>, <xref target="table-ecdh-es-parameter-table"/>.
          The specification column for all rows in that table should be this document.
        </t>

      </section>
      <section anchor="cose-algorithm-registry" title="COSE Algorithm Registry">

        <t>
          It is requested that IANA create a new registry entitled “COSE Algorithm Registry”.
        </t>

        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText='The columns of the registry are:'>
              
            </t>
            <t hangText='value'>
              The value to be used to identify this algorithm.
              Algorithm values MUST be unique.
              The value can be a positive integer, a negative integer or a string.
              Integer values between 0 and 255 and strings of length 1 are designated as Standards Track Document required.
              Integer values from 256 to 65535 and strings of length 2 are designated as Specification Required.
              Integer values of greater than 65535 and strings of length greater than 2 are designated as first come first server.
              Integer values in the range -1 to -65536 are delegated to the “COSE Header Algorithm Label” registry.
              Integer values beyond -65536 are marked as private use.
            </t>
            <t hangText='description'>
              A short description of the algorithm.
            </t>
            <t hangText='specification'>
              A document where the algorithm is defined (if publicly available).
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>
          The initial contents of the registry can be found in the following:
          <xref target="table-AES-CCM"/>, <xref target="table-AES-GCM"/>, <xref target="Table-CHACHA"/>, <xref target="table_ecdsa"/>, <xref target="table-rsa-algs"/>, <xref target="table-hmac"/>, <xref target="table-aes-mac"/>, <xref target="table-direct"/>, <xref target="table-direct-kdf"/>, <xref target="table_aes_keywrap"/>, <xref target="table-RSA-OAEP"/>, <xref target="table-ecdh-es-table"/>.
          The specification column for all rows in that table should be this document.
        </t>

      </section>
      <section anchor="cose-key-map-registry" title="COSE Key Common Parameter Registry">

        <t>
          It is requested that IANA create a new registry entitled “COSE Key Common Parameter" Registry.
        </t>

        <t>
          The columns of the registry are:
        </t>

        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText='name'>
              This is a descriptive name that enables easier reference to the item.  It is not used in the encoding.
            </t>
            <t hangText='label'>
              The value to be used to identify this algorithm.
              Key map labels MUST be unique.
              The label can be a positive integer, a negative integer or a string.
              Integer values between 0 and 255 and strings of length 1 are designated as Standards Track Document required.
              Integer values from 256 to 65535 and strings of length 2 are designated as Specification Required.
              Integer values of greater than 65535 and strings of length greater than 2 are designated as first come first server.
              Integer values in the range -1 to -65536 are used for key parameters specific to a single algorithm delegated to the “COSE Key Parameter Label” registry.
              Integer values beyond -65536 are marked as private use.
            </t>
            <t hangText='CBOR Type'>
              This field contains the CBOR type for the field
            </t>
            <t hangText='registry'>
              This field denotes the registry that values come from, if one exists.
            </t>
            <t hangText='description'>
              This field contains a brief description for the field
            </t>
            <t hangText='specification'>
              This contains a pointer to the public specification for the field if one exists
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>
          This registry will be initially populated by the values in <xref target="COSE_KEY_KEYS"/>.
          The specification column for all of these entries will be this document.
        </t>

      </section>

      
      <section anchor="cose-key-parameter-registry" title="COSE Key Type Parameter Registry">

        <t>
          It is requested that IANA create a new registry “COSE Key Type Parameters”.
        </t>

        <t>
          The columns of the table are:
        </t>

        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText='key type'>
              This field contains a descriptive string of a key type. 
              This should be a value that is in the COSE General Values table and is placed in the 'kty' field of a COSE Key structure.
            </t>
            <t hangText='name'>
              This is a descriptive name that enables easier reference to the item.  It is not used in the encoding.
            </t>
            <t hangText='label'>
              The label is to be unique for every value of key type. 
              The range of values is from -256 to -1.
              Labels are expected to be reused for different keys.
            </t>
            <t hangText='CBOR type'>
              This field contains the CBOR type for the field
            </t>
            <t hangText='description'>
              This field contains a brief description for the field
            </t>
            <t hangText='specification'>
              This contains a pointer to the public specification for the field if one exists
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>
          This registry will be initially populated by the values in <xref target="table-ec2-keys"/>, <xref target="table-rsa-keys"/>, and <xref target="table-symmetric-keys"/>.
          The specification column for all of these entries will be this document.
        </t>

      </section>

      <section anchor="cose-curve-registry" title="COSE Elliptic Curve Registry">

        <t>
          It is requested that IANA create a new registry “COSE Elliptic Curve Parameters”.
        </t>

        <t>
          The columns of the table are:
        </t>

        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText='name'>
              This is a descriptive name that enables easier reference to the item.  
              It is not used in the encoding.
            </t>
            <t hangText='value'>
              This is the value used to identify the curve.
              These values MUST be unique.
              The integer values from -256 to 255 are designated as Standards Track Document Required.
              The the integer values from 256 to 65535 and -65536 to -257 are designated as Specification Required.
              Integer values over 65535 are designated as first come first serve.
              Integer values less than -65536 are marked as private use.
            </t>
            <t hangText='key type'>
              This designates the key type(s) that can be used with this curve.
            </t>
            <t hangText='description'>
              This field contains a brief description of the curve.
            </t>
            <t hangText='specification'>
              This contains a pointer to the public specification for the curve if one exists.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>
          This registry will be initially populated by the values in <xref target="table_key_types"/>.
          The specification column for all of these entries will be this document.
        </t>


      </section>

      <section title="Media Type Registration">

        <section title="COSE Security Message">

          <t>
            This section registers the "application/cose" and "application/cose+cbor" media types in the "Media Types" registry.
            <cref source="JLS">Should we register both or just the cose+cbor one?</cref>
            These media types are used to indicate that the content is a COSE_MSG.
          </t>

          <t>
          <list style="none">
            <t>Type name: application</t>
            <t>Subtype name: cose</t>
            <t>Required parameters: N/A</t>
            <t>Optional parameters: N/A</t>
            <t>Encoding considerations: binary</t>
            <t>Security considerations: See the Security Considerations section of RFC TBD.</t>
            <t>Interoperability considerations: N/A</t>
            <t>Published specification: RFC TBD</t>
            <t>Applications that use this media type: To be identified</t>
            <t>Fragment identifier considerations: N/A</t>
            <t>Additional information:
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>Magic number(s): N/A</t>
              <t>File extension(s): cbor</t>
              <t>Macintosh file type code(s): N/A</t>
            </list>
            </t>
            <t>Person &amp; email address to contact for further information: iesg@ietf.org</t>
            <t>Intended usage: COMMON</t>
            <t>Restrictions on usage: N/A</t>
            <t>Author: Jim Schaad, ietf@augustcellars.com</t>
            <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>
            <t>Provisional registration?  No</t>
          </list>
          </t>

          <t>
          <list style="non">
            <t>Type name: application</t>
            <t>Subtype name: cose+cbor</t>
            <t>Required parameters: N/A</t>
            <t>Optional parameters: N/A</t>
            <t>Encoding considerations: binary</t>
            <t>Security considerations: See the Security Considerations section of RFC TBD.</t>
            <t>Interoperability considerations: N/A</t>
            <t>Published specification: RFC TBD</t>
            <t>Applications that use this media type: To be identified</t>
            <t>Fragment identifier considerations: N/A</t>
            <t>Additional information:
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>Magic number(s): N/A</t>
              <t>File extension(s): cbor</t>
              <t>Macintosh file type code(s): N/A</t>
            </list>
            </t>
            <t>Person &amp; email address to contact for further information: iesg@ietf.org</t>
            <t>Intended usage: COMMON</t>
            <t>Restrictions on usage: N/A</t>
            <t>Author: Jim Schaad, ietf@augustcellars.com</t>
            <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>
            <t>Provisional registration?  No</t>
          </list>
          </t>

        </section>
        <section title="COSE Key media type">

          <t>
            This section registers the "application/cose+json" and "application/cose-set+json" media types in the "Media Types" registry.
            These media types are used to indicate, respectively, that content is a COSE_Key or COSE_KeySet object.
          </t>

          <t>
          <list style="non">
            <t>Type name: application</t>
            <t>Subtype name: cose-key+cbor</t>
            <t>Required parameters: N/A</t>
            <t>Optional parameters: N/A</t>
            <t>Encoding considerations: binary</t>
            <t>Security considerations: See the Security Considerations section of RFC TBD.</t>
            <t>Interoperability considerations: N/A</t>
            <t>Published specification: RFC TBD</t>
            <t>Applications that use this media type: To be identified</t>
            <t>Fragment identifier considerations: N/A</t>
            <t>Additional information:
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>Magic number(s): N/A</t>
              <t>File extension(s): cbor</t>
              <t>Macintosh file type code(s): N/A</t>
            </list>
            </t>
            <t>Person &amp; email address to contact for further information: iesg@ietf.org</t>
            <t>Intended usage: COMMON</t>
            <t>Restrictions on usage: N/A</t>
            <t>Author: Jim Schaad, ietf@augustcellars.com</t>
            <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>
            <t>Provisional registration?  No</t>
          </list>
          </t>

          <t>
          <list style="none">
            <t>Type name: application</t>
            <t>Subtype name: cose-key-set+cbor</t>
            <t>Required parameters: N/A</t>
            <t>Optional parameters: N/A</t>
            <t>Encoding considerations: binary</t>
            <t>Security considerations: See the Security Considerations section of RFC TBD.</t>
            <t>Interoperability considerations: N/A</t>
            <t>Published specification: RFC TBD</t>
            <t>Applications that use this media type: To be identified</t>
            <t>Fragment identifier considerations: N/A</t>
            <t>Additional information:
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>Magic number(s): N/A</t>
              <t>File extension(s): cbor</t>
              <t>Macintosh file type code(s): N/A</t>
            </list>
            </t>
            <t>Person &amp; email address to contact for further information: iesg@ietf.org</t>
            <t>Intended usage: COMMON</t>
            <t>Restrictions on usage: N/A</t>
            <t>Author: Jim Schaad, ietf@augustcellars.com</t>
            <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>
            <t>Provisional registration?  No</t>
          </list>
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security-considerations" title="Security Considerations">

      <t>
        There are security considerations:
      </t>

      <t>
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>
            Protect private keys
          </t>
          <t>
            MAC messages with more than one recipient means one cannot figure out who sent the message
          </t>
          <t>
            Use of direct key with other recipient structures hands the key to other recipients.
          </t>
          <t>
            Use of direct ECDH direct encryption is easy for people to leak information on if there are other recipients in the message.
          </t>
          <t>
            Considerations about protected vs unprotected header fields.
          </t>
          <t>
            Need to verify that:
            1) the kty field of the key matches the key and algorithm being used. 
            2) that the kty field needs to be included in the trust decision as well as the other key fields.
            3) that the algorithm be included in the trust decision.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

    </section>


  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title='Normative References'>
      &RFC2119;
      &RFC7049;
    </references>

    <references title='Informative References'>
      &CDDL;
      <!-- &CBCMAC; -->
      &RFC2104;
      &RFC2633;
      &RFC2898;
      &RFC3394;
      &RFC3447;
      &RFC3610;
      &RFC4231;
      &RFC4262;
      &RFC5480;
      &RFC5652;
      &RFC5751;
      &RFC5752;
      &RFC5869;
      &RFC5990;
      &RFC6090;
      &RFC6151;
      &RFC6979;
      &RFC7159;
      &RFC7252;
      &RFC7515;
      &RFC7516;
      &RFC7517;
      &RFC7518;
      &RFC7539;
      
      <!-- &CFRG-EC; -->

      <reference anchor="AES-GCM" >
        <front>
          <title>NIST Special Publication 800-38D: Recommendation for Block Cipher Modes of Operation: Galois/Counter Mode (GCM) and GMAC.</title>
          <author initials="M." surname="Dworkin">
            <organization>U.S. National Institute of Standards and Technology</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2007" month="Nov"/>
        </front>
        <format target="https://csrc.nist.gov/publications/nistpubs/800-38D/SP-800-38D.pdf" type="PDF"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="MAC">
        <front>
          <title>FIPS PUB 113: Computer Data Authentication</title>
          <author initials="N" surname="NiST"/>
          <date year="1985" month="May"/>
        </front>
        <format target="http://csrc.nist.gov/publications/fips/fips113/fips113.html" type="HTML"/>
      </reference>
      
      <reference anchor="DSS">
        <front>
          <title>Digital Signature Standard (DSS)</title>
          <author>
            <organization>U.S. National Institute of Standards and Technology</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2013" month="July"/>
        </front>
        <format target="http://nvlpubs.nist.gov/nistpubs/FIPS/NIST.FIPS.186-4.pdf" type="PDF"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="SP800-56A">
        <front>
          <title>NIST Special Publication 800-56A: Recommendation for Pair-Wise Key Establishment Schemes Using Discrete Logarithm Cryptography</title>
          <author initials="E." surname="Barker">
            <organization>U.S. National Institute of Standards and Technology</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="L." surname="Chen">
            <organization>U.S. National Institute of Standards and Technology</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="A." surname="Roginsky">
            <organization>U.S. National Institute of Standards and Technology</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="M." surname="Smid">
            <organization>Orion Security Solutions, Inc.</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2013" month="May"/>
        </front>
        <format target="https://nvlpubs.nist.gov/nistpubs/SpecialPublications/NIST.SP.800-56Ar2.pdf" type="PDF"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="SEC1">
        <front>
          <title>SEC 1: Elliptic Curve Cryptography</title>
          <author>
            <organization>Standards for Efficient Cryptography Group</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2009" month="May"/>
        </front>
        <format target="http://www.secg.org/sec1-v2.pdf" type="PDF"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="MultiPrimeRSA">
        <front>
          <title>On the Security of Multi-prime RSA</title>
          <author initials="M. J." surname="Hinek">
            <organization>University of Waterloo</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="D. R." surname="Cheriton">
            <organization>University of Waterloo</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2006" month="June"/>
        </front>
        <format target="http://cacr.uwaterloo.ca/techreports/2006/cacr2006-16.pdf" type="PDF"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="PVSig">
        <front>
          <title>Formal Security Proofs for a Signature Scheme with Partial Message Recover</title>
          <author initials="D." surname="Brown">
          </author>
          <author initials="D." surname="Johnson">
          </author>
          <date year="2000" month="February"/>
        </front>
        <format target="https://www.certicom.com/images/pdfs/CerticomWP-PVSigSec_login.pdf" type="PDF"/>
      </reference>

    </references>

    <!--
        I think this can go away because the text in the encryption section went away as well.
        
    <section anchor="AE-algo" title="AEAD and AE algorithms">

      <t>
        The set of encryption algorithms that can be used with this
        specification is restricted to authenticated encryption (AE) and
        authenticated encryption with additional data (AEAD) algorithms.
        This means that there is a strong check that the data decrypted by the
        recipient is the same as what was encrypted by the sender.
        Encryption modes such as counter have no check on this at all.
        The CBC encryption mode had a weak check that the data is correct,
        given a random key and random data, the CBC padding check will pass
        one out of 256 times.
        There have been several times that a normal encryption mode has been
        combined with an integrity check to provide a content encryption mode
        that does provide the necessary authentication.
        AES-GCM <xref target="AES-GCM"/>, AES-CCM <xref target="RFC3610"/>, AES-CBC-HMAC
        <xref target="I-D.mcgrew-aead-aes-cbc-hmac-sha2"/> are  examples of these composite
        modes.
      </t>

      <t>
        PKCS v1.5 RSA key transport does not qualify as an AE algorithm.
        There are only three bytes in the encoding that can be checked as
        having decrypted correctly, the rest of the content can only be
        probabilistically checked as having decrypted correctly.
        For this reason, PKCS v1.5 RSA key transport MUST NOT be used with
        this specification.
        RSA-OAEP was designed to have the necessary checks that that content
        correctly decrypted and does qualify as an AE algorithm.
      </t>

      <t>
        When dealing with authenticated encryption algorithms, there is always some type of value that needs to be checked to see if the authentication level has passed.
        This authentication value may be:
      </t>

      <t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            A separately generated tag computed by both the encrypter and decrypter and then compared by the decryptor.
            This tag value may be either placed at the end of the cipher text (the decision we made) or kept separately (the decision made by the JOSE working group).
            This is the approach followed by AES-GCM <xref target="AES-GCM"/> and AES-CCM <xref target="RFC3610"/>.
            <! - - Mike Jones:  Last sentence is not clear.  He is reading this as referring to ? rather than just being generating a tag. - M00TODO - - >
          </t>
          <t>
            A fixed value that is part of the encoded plain text.
            This is the approach followed by the AES key wrap algorithm <xref target="RFC3394"/>.
          </t>
          <t>
            A computed value is included as part of the encoded plain text.
            The computed value is then checked by the decryptor using the same computation path.
            This is the approach followed by RSAES-OAEP <xref target="RFC3447"/>.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

    </section>

        -->

    <section anchor="Grammar_Appendix" title="CDDL Grammar">

      <t>
        For people who prefer using a formal language to describe the syntax of the CBOR, in this section a CDDL grammar is given that corresponds to <xref target="I-D.greevenbosch-appsawg-cbor-cddl"/>.
        This grammar is informational, in the event of differences between this grammar and the prose, the prose is considered to be authorative.
      </t>
      
      <t>
        The collected CDDL can be extracted from the XML version of this document via the following XPath expression below.
        (Depending on the XPath evaluator one is using, it may be necessary to deal with &amp;gt; as an entity.)
      </t>

      <t>
        <figure><artwork type='XPATH'>
<![CDATA[
//artwork[@type='CDDL']/text()
]]></artwork></figure>         
      </t>
      
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="three-layer" title="Three Levels of Recipient Information">

      <t>
        All of the currently defined recipient algorithms classes only use two levels of the COSE_Encrypt structure.
        The first level is the message content and the second level is the content key encryption.
        However, if one uses a recipient algorithm such as RSA-KEM (see Appendix A of RSA-KEM <xref target="RFC5990"/>, then it make sense to have three levels of the COSE_Encrypt structure.
      </t>

      <t>
        These levels would be:

        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            Level 0: The content encryption level.  This level contains the payload of the message.
          </t>
          <t>
            Level 1: The encryption of the CEK by a KEK.
          </t>
          <t>
            Level 2: The encryption of a long random secret using an RSA key and a key derivation function to convert that secret into the KEK.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>
        This is an example of what a triple layer message would look like.
        The message has the following layers:

        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            Level 0: Has a content encrypted with AES-GCM using a 128-bit key.
          </t>
          <t>
            Level 1: Uses the AES Key wrap algorithm with a 128-bit key.
          </t>
          <t>
            Level 2: Uses ECDH Ephemeral-Static direct to generate the level 1 key.
          </t>
        </list>

        In effect this example is a decomposed version of using the ECDH-ES+A128KW algorithm.
      </t>

      &Triple-01;

    </section>


    <section anchor="examples" title="Examples">

      <t>
        The examples can be found at https://github.com/cose-wg/Examples.  The file names in each section correspond the the same file names in the repository. I am currently still in the process of getting the examples up there along with some control information for people to be able to check and reproduce the examples.
      </t>

      <t>
        Examples may have some features that are in questions but not yet incorporated in the document.
      </t>

      <t>
        To make it easier to read, the examples are presented using the CBOR's diagnostic notation rather than a binary dump.
        A ruby based tool exists to convert between a number of formats.
        This tool can be installed with the command line:
      </t>
      <figure>
        <artwork>
        <![CDATA[gem install cbor-diag]]>
        </artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>
        The diagnostic notation can be converted into binary files using the following command line:
      </t>
      <figure><artwork>
<![CDATA[          
         diag2cbor < inputfile > outputfile
         ]]>
      </artwork></figure>

      <t>
        The examples can be extracted from the XML version of this docuent via an XPath expression as all of the artwork is tagged with the attribute  type='CBORdiag'.
      </t>

      <section title="Examples of MAC messages">
        
        <section anchor="Mac-04" title="Shared Secret Direct MAC">
          <t>
            This example users the following:
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>MAC: AES-CMAC, 256-bit key, trucated to 64 bits</t>
              <t>Recipient class: direct shared secret</t>
              <t>File name: Mac-04</t>
            </list>
          </t>

          &Mac-04;
        </section>
        
        <section anchor="Mac-01" title="ECDH Direct MAC">

          <t>
            This example uses the following:
            
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>MAC: HMAC w/SHA-256, 256-bit key
              </t>
              <t>Recipient class: ECDH key agreement, two static keys, HKDF w/ context structure</t>
            </list>
          </t>

          &Mac-01;

        </section>
        <section anchor="Mac-02" title="Wrapped MAC">

          <t>
            This example uses the following:

            <list style="symbols">
              <t>MAC: AES-MAC, 128-bit key, truncated to 64 bits</t>
              <t>Recipient class: AES keywrap w/ a pre-shared 256-bit key</t>
            </list>
          </t>

          &Mac-02;

        </section>

        <section anchor="Mac-03" title="Multi-recipient MAC message">

          <t>
            This example uses the following:

            <list style="symbols">
              <t>MAC: HMAC w/ SHA-256, 128-bit key</t>
              <t>
                Recipient class: Uses three different methods
                <list style="numbers">
                  <t>ECDH Ephemeral-Static, Curve P-521, AES-Key Wrap w/ 128-bit key</t>
                  <t>RSA-OAEP w/ SHA-256</t>
                  <t>AES-Key Wrap w/ 256-bit key</t>
                </list>
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>

          &Mac-03;

        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Examples of Encrypted Messages">
        
        <section anchor="Enc-01" title="Direct ECDH">

          <t>
            This example uses the following:

            <list style="symbols">
              <t>CEK: AES-GCM w/ 128-bit key</t>
              <t>Recipient class: ECDH Ephemeral-Static, Curve P-256</t>
            </list>
          </t>
          
          &Enc-01;

        </section>

        <section anchor="Enc-02" title="Direct plus Key Derivation">
          <t>
            This example uses the following:
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>CEK: AES-CCM w/128-bit key, trucate the tag to 64-bits</t>
              <t>Recipient class: Use HKDF on a shared secret with the following implicit fields as part of the context.
              <list style="symbols">
                <t>APU identity: "lighting-client"</t>
                <t>APV identity: "lighting-server"</t>
                <t>Supplimentary Public Other: "Encryption Example 02"</t>
              </list>
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>

          &Enc-02;
          
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Examples of Signed Message">
        <section anchor="Sig-01" title="Single Signature">

          <t>
            This example uses the following:

            <list style="symbols">
              <t>Signature Algorithm: RSA-PSS w/ SHA-384, MGF-1</t>
            </list>
          </t>

          &Sig-01;

        </section>


        <section anchor="Sig-02" title="Multiple Signers">

          <t>
            This example uses the following:

            <list style="symbols">
              <t>Signature Algorithm: RSA-PSS w/ SHA-256, MGF-1</t>
              <t>Signature Algorithm: ECDSA w/ SHA-512, Curve P-521</t>
            </list>
          </t>

          &Sig-02;

        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="COSE Keys">
        <section title="Public Keys">
          <t>
            This is an example of a COSE Key set.
            This example includes the public keys for all of the previous examples.
          </t>

          <t>
            In order the keys are:
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>An EC key with a kid of "meriadoc.brandybuck@buckland.example"</t>
              <t>An EC key with a kid of "peregrin.took@tuckborough.example"</t>
              <t>An EC key with a kid of "bilbo.baggins@hobbiton.example"</t>
              <t>An RSA key with a kid of "bilbo.baggins@hobbiton.example"</t>
            </list>
          </t>
          
          &PubKeys;
        </section>

        <section title="Private Keys">
          <t>
            This is an example of a COSE Key set.
            This example includes the private keys for all of the previous examples.
          </t>

          <t>
            In order the keys are:
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>An EC key with a kid of "meriadoc.brandybuck@buckland.example"</t>
              <t>A shared-secret key with a kid of "our-secret"</t>
              <t>An EC key with a kid of "peregrin.took@tuckborough.example"</t>
              <t>A shared-secret key with a kid of "018c0ae5-4d9b-471b-bfd6-eef314bc7037"</t>
              <t>An EC key with a kid of "bilbo.baggins@hobbiton.example"</t>
              <t>An RSA key with a kid of "bilbo.baggins@hobbiton.example"</t>
            </list>
          </t>


          &PrivKeys;
        </section>
        </section>
    </section>

    <!--
        PBSE2 went away

    <section anchor="Header-Algorithm-Table" title="COSE Header Algorithm Label Table">

      <t> This section disappears when we make a decision on password based key management.</t>
      <texttable>
        <ttcol align='left'>name</ttcol>
        <ttcol align='left'>algorithm</ttcol>
        <ttcol align='left'>label</ttcol>
        <ttcol align='left'>CBOR type</ttcol>
        <ttcol align='left'>description</ttcol>
        <c>p2c</c>        <c>PBE</c>        <c>-1</c>        <c>int</c>        <c></c>
        <c>p2s</c>        <c>PBE</c>        <c>-2</c>        <c>bstr</c>        <c></c>
      </texttable>

    </section>
    -->

    <section title="Document Updates">
      <!-- RFC Editor - Please remove this appendix before publishing -->
      <section title="Version -05 to -06">
        <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>Remove new CFRG Elliptical Curve key agreement algorithms.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Version -04 to -05">
        <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>Removed the jku, x5c, x5t, x5t#S256, x5u, and jwk headers.</t>
            <t>Add enveloped data vs encrypted data structures.</t>
            <t>Add counter signature parameter.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Version -03 to -04">
        <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>Change top level from map to array.</t>
            <t>Eliminate the term "key managment" from the document.</t>
            <t>Point to content registries for the 'content type' attribute</t>
            <t>Push protected field into the KDF functions for recipients.</t>
            <t>Remove password based recipient information.</t>
            <t>Create EC Curve Registry.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Version -02 to -03">
        <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>Make a pass over all of the algorithm text.</t>
            <t>Alter the CDDL so that Keys and KeySets are top level items and the key examples validate.</t>
            <t>Add sample key structures.</t>
            <t>Expand text on dealing with Externally Supplied Data.</t>
            <t>Update the examples to match some of the renumbering of fields.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Version -02 to -03">
        <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>Add a set of straw man proposals for algorithms.  It is possible/expected that this text will be moved to a new document.</t>
            <t>Add a set of straw man proposals for key structures.  It is possible/expected that this text will be moved to a new document.</t>
            <t>Provide guidance on use of externally supplied authenticated data.</t>
            <t>Add external authenticated data to signing structure.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Version -01 to -2">
        <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>Add first pass of algorithm information</t>
            <t>Add direct key derivation example.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Version -00 to -01">
        <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>Add note on where the document is being maintained and contributing notes.</t>
            <t>Put in proposal on MTI algorithms.</t>
            <t>Changed to use labels rather than keys when talking about what indexes a map.</t>
            <t>Moved nonce/IV to be a common header item.</t>
            <t>Expand section to discuss the common set of labels used in COSE_Key maps.</t>
            <t>Start marking element 0 in registries as reserved.</t>
            <t>Update examples.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
